<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Theanthropos: or, God made man. A tract proving the nativity of our Saviour to be on the 25. of December. / By John Selden, that eminently-learned antiquary, late of the Inner-Temple.</title>
            <author>Selden, John, 1584-1654.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 191 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92878</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2439</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1809_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203528</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863464</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863464</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115666</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92878)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115666)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 225:E1809[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Theanthropos: or, God made man. A tract proving the nativity of our Saviour to be on the 25. of December. / By John Selden, that eminently-learned antiquary, late of the Inner-Temple.</title>
                  <author>Selden, John, 1584-1654.</author>
                  <author>Chantry, John, d. 1662?, engraver.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 91, [21] p. : port. (metal cut)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.G. for Nathaniel Brooks at the Angel in Corn-hill.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First word of title in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>The portrait of the author is signed: I: Chantry: scu.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Date of birth --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Nativity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115666:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ΘΕΑΝΘΡΩΠΟΣ: OR, God made Man. A TRACT PROVING <hi>THE NATIVITY</hi> OF OUR SAVIOUR to be on the 25. of December.</p>
            <p>By JOHN SELDEN, that eminently-learned Antiquary, late of the <hi>Inner-Temple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J.G.</hi> for <hi>Nathaniel Brooks</hi> at the Angel in <hi>Corn-hill.</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:115666:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115666:2"/>
            <head>TO THE LEARNED GENTRY OF THE INNER TEMPLE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ere is not to comply with the mode of the Times, an Epiſtle had been altogether uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs; for to expatiate upon his deſert, were but <hi>actum agere,</hi> ſince the Britiſh world has been ſufficiently ſenſible thereof. <hi>Opus authoris nomine inſignitur;</hi> The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors name in the Frontispiece commends the work above my ability, and will ſave me a labour. Now that this was the legitimate iſſue of famous <hi>Seldens</hi> brain is indisputable, ſince he that is never ſo meanly acquainted with the ſtyle, will ſoon acknowledge it. 'Twere pitty that ſo elaborate a Treatiſe ſhould ſleep in the grave of oblivion; especially, when there are ſo many perſons in this age, (whoſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guided zeal chriſtens all that thwarts the grain of their phanatique opinions with the nick-name of ſuperſtition) that do ſo much oppugne the ſubject and verity of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; but, beyond all controverſy, they that peruſe it muſt be convinced or manifeſt themſelves obſtinately ſtubborn. 'Tis a miſtery to me that I could never fathom, to imagine that any <hi>Levite</hi> ſhould rely ſo much upon Chriſt for ſalvation; and yet deny, nay, be offended at the celebrations of his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity: But, if either Divine or Humane authority the practiſe of the Primitive times, or the Inſtitution of our Holy Mother the Church of <hi>England,</hi> carry ſtrength or prevalency along with them, I am confident of their recan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.
<pb facs="tcp:115666:3"/>This aboliſhing of decency and ſolemniſations, hath quite conſumed the ſubſtance of Religion; and the ſad ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects thereof, have been of late years too too apparent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us; Inſtead of endeavouring to order, they did ordure the Houſe of God; Temples were turn'd into Stercoraries, into a confuſion. But now, ſince it hath pleas'd the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Architect of Heaven and Earth, that tranſoplves Crowns, and tumbles down Diadems at his pleaſure, to make us meet together like ſo many lines in the centre (that have been ſo long eccomrique both in the Eccleſiaſtique and Politique capacity,) there is a certainty of a reſettlement of Eccleſiaſtique affairs according to the old and true form of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> To which this Tractate if it conduce not, I preſume 'twill no ways impede it; ſince it is not only ſolid but full fraught with variety of learning; inſomuch that it will require three lives in the Law at leaſt to purchaſe, and peruſe thoſe printed pieces, and manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripts, out of which he hath collected his quotations: But I muſt not be ſo uncivil as to detain you too long in the Porch by a prolixe Epiſtle; nor ſo injurious to withhold you from prying into the more ſublime and refined ſenſe of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor: Now if your poruſall be with as much candor, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ty and moderation, as the learned <hi>Selden</hi> penned it, (though now deceaſed) 'will certainly force you to acquieſce with him, and affirm, That the day of the Nativity of our Saviour is not onely to be celebrated, but alſo abſolutely, and undeniably on the <hi>25.</hi> of <hi>December.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:115666:3"/>
            <head>The Contents of this Tract.</head>
            <head>Of the Birth-day of our SAVIOUR.</head>
            <list>
               <item>BRiefly, of the Anniverſary Celebration of Birth-days: The ſtate of the Queſtion, and this Diſcourſe digeſted into parts. pag. 1</item>
               <item>SECT. I. The Authority of keeping it on this day both in the Eaſtern and Weſtern Churches about 400. years after our Saviours; and that then it was ancient in the Weſtern Church, and known alſo under the name of the Winter-Solſtice-day; which is eſpecially here obſervable. pag. 7</item>
               <item>SECT. II. For preparation of more particular proof of the Tradition of this Feaſt-day, the ſuppoſition which the moſt Primitive Ages had touching the time of the Solſtices and Aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxes. pag. 13</item>
               <item>SECT. III. That the keeping it on this day was ſo receiv'd from tradition, even of the eldeſt times ſince our Saviour; and this juſtified from the Fathers, ſuppoſing it to have been on the very day of the ancient Winter-Solſtice. pag. 21</item>
               <item>SECT. IV. Expreſſe teſtimonies to the ſame purpoſe out of ancient Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and a Confirmation from the generall uſe in the ſeverall Churches of Chriſtendome. pag. 32</item>
               <item>SECT. V. The common Reaſons uſed out of the holy Text to juſtifie this day, and how they are miſtaken, and therefore not uſed
<pb facs="tcp:115666:4"/>here; together with what ſome would prove from the Scheme of his Nativity. pag. 45</item>
               <item>SECT. VI. The chief Objections that are made againſt this day being the true time of the birth, with plain anſwers to them. pag. 56</item>
               <item>SECT. VII. Some other opinions among the ancients touching it, and how ſome of them may agree with what we have received, and the reſt are of no weight againſt it; and there more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of the ancient confuſion of this Feaſt with that of the <hi>Epiphany.</hi> pag. 77</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="epitaph">
            <pb facs="tcp:115666:4"/>
            <head>JOANNIS SELDENI EPITAPHIUM.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Joannes Seldenus</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Heic juxta ſitus;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Natus eſt XVI Decembris MDLXXXIV</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Salvintoniae;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Qui viculus eſt Terring Occidentalis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>in Suſſexiae Maritimis;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Parentibus honeſtis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Joanne Seldeno Thomae filio,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>è Quinis ſecundo.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Anno MDXLI nate,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Margareta filiâ &amp; Haerede unicâ Thomae</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bakeri de Ruſhington ex Equeſtri Bakero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum in Cantio familiâ, filius è cunis ſuperſtitum unicus, Aetatis ferè</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>LXX annorum.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Denatus eſt ultime die Novembris,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Anno ſalutis reparatae</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>MDCLIV.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Per quam expectat heic Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectionem felicem.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:115666:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115666:5"/>
            <head>Of the Birth-day of our SAVIOUR. <hi>Briefly, of the Anniverſary Celebration of Birth-dayes: The ſtate of the Queſtion, and this Diſcourſe digeſted into parts.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the review of the 4 <hi>Chap.</hi> having occaſion to ſpeak of the authority of the <hi>Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines,</hi> the eighth book of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, attributed to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, in which an expreſſe conſtitution is, that the Birth-day of our Saviour ſhould be celebrated on the 25 of <hi>December</hi> (or of the ninth month, as it is there called, being accounted from <hi>April</hi> as the firſt) I noted that Conſtitution for one character of that volum's being ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſititious; in regard that in the Eaſtern Church (where thoſe Conſtitutions being in Greek muſt by all probability have been in moſt uſe) the Celebration of that day was not received on the 25 of <hi>December,</hi> till the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient tradition of it was learn'd from the Weſtern, about 400 years after Chriſt;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115666:6"/>and ſome touch alſo I have there of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of them that think that day not to be the true time of his birth. This paſſage hath been ſo conceiv'd as if I had purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call'd in queſtion the celebration of that ſacred day (which is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tom.</hi> 7. <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. Saviliana,</hi> page 375. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſtyles it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, as the main fort of all happineſſe, and the fountain and root of all good that we enjoy; and to call it in queſtion, as if I ſuppoſed it were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd at that time without ſufficient ground, and as if I were too inclining to the part of the hot-brain'd and diſturbing Puritans, which impiouſly deny the keeping of a day as an anniverſary feaſt conſecrated to the birth of our bleſſed Saviour; from which my conſcience was ever, and is moſt clearly free. For I knew, firſt, both from ſacred &amp; profane Story, that the anniverſary dayes,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">200 <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſ.</hi> &amp; <hi>Juſtin. de feriis. Sed de hac re plenè Martinus de Roa lib. de die Natali.</hi>
               </note> not only of Princes, but of ſome private men alſo, were with frequency ever obſerv'd, and the beginning of Cities un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that name yearly celebrated: and even among the Heathen, thoſe that profeſſed ſuch Philoſophy as was neareſt to true Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, that is, the <hi>Platoniſts,</hi> were moſt reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious in keeping their <hi>Plato's</hi> birth-day, which they received by tradition to be the
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Laertius in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Plat. &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> ſame with <hi>Apollo's,</hi> that is, the 7. day of the Attique moneth <hi>Thargelion</hi> (which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to our <hi>April:</hi>) and this was ſtill ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115666:6"/>until the time of <hi>Plotinus</hi> and
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Marſil. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinus comment. ad Plat. Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſ. cap.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyry,</hi> who lived about 270 years after our Saviours birth; and after the diſcontinuance of it for many ages, it was revived in the dayes of our Grand-fathers with much ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity in the Dutchy of <hi>Florence</hi> by <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renzo Medices.</hi> But he miſplaced it in the year, while he and his gueſts being better <hi>Platoniſts</hi> than Chronologers, took the 7 of <hi>Thargelion</hi> to be the 7 of <hi>November:</hi> As alſo the old trifling Aſtrologers committed a like fault, while in the ſcheme
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Firmicus Matheſ. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 30.</note> of his Nativity they place the Sun in <hi>Piſces,</hi> which muſt denote our <hi>February,</hi> or the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique <hi>Antheſterion.</hi> But however, an anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary day was obſerv'd for his Birth: ſo was there anciently for the birth of ſome falſe Gods; for they had their certain days for the births of
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Calend. vet. Rom. à G. Herwarto, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per editum, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Mars, Apollo, Diana, Minerva,</hi> the <hi>Muſes, Hercules,</hi> and others, and carefully obſerv'd them; and for Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and private perſons, even to this day a celebration is in uſe at the yearly returning of their Birth-days. To deny therefore, with that way-ward Sect, ſuch an anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary honour to the Saviour of the World, were but to think him leſſe worthy of it than falſe Gods were eſteemed by the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, than Princes by their Subjects, than private friends by their greater friends, whoſe birth-dayes they yearly celebrated. But of this I truſt no man that truly deſerves a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115666:7"/>name among Chriſtians will make ſcruple. Some indeed (and thoſe not a few among the learned) have doubted of the juſt time of the birth of our Saviour; which while they doubt, they offer the more occaſion to others to queſtion and impugne the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebration of it, as it is now ſetled in the Church; For if that were not the true day (as they argue) it follows that there were no more reaſon (ſave only what comes from the latter, and arbitrary conſtitutions of the Church) to keep that day than any other throughout the whole year, unleſs alſo ſome other day were found to be the exact time of it. But for my ſelf here, as I was far from queſtioning the duty of it, ſo was I alſo from doubting of the right of Celebration of it on the very day of <hi>December</hi> whereon it is now kept. And to make clear my mind here, I ſhall now more largely, according to what <hi>His Majeſties</hi> moſt learned inſtructions have taught me, declare the certainty of that feaſt, as it is at this day obſerved, even from the eldeſt of the Chriſtian times, and Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal tradition, received even from the practice of his Diſciples; for it is one thing to deny (as I have done) that it was ſo ordained by the Apoſtles in thoſe <hi>Clementines,</hi> (which I think all learned and ingenuous men will deny) and another and far-different thing to affirm, that the tradition of that day, as it is now kept, is both Apoſtolical, and as ancient as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115666:7"/>the birth it ſelf; as I ſhall preſently deliver in the deduction of the continuance of it, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as it is now obſerved through all Chriſtendom. For although in the feaſt, and in all others unmoveable, there be the known difference of ten dayes (which were taken out of <hi>Octob.</hi> in the year MDLXXXII
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Conſtit. ſum. Pontif. p.</hi> 775. <hi>&amp; Clavius in Kal. Greg. ſive tom.</hi> 5.</note> by Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the Thirteenth, when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the <hi>Julian Kalendar</hi>) 'twixt us, with ſome few other States, and thoſe which have received the <hi>Gregorian Kalendar;</hi> yet both they and we agree in this, that upon the 25. of that Moneth (that is with us of our <hi>Julian December</hi>) this feaſt is ever to be obſerved. So that we meddle not here at all with any part of the differences 'twixt the <hi>Julian</hi> and <hi>Gregorian</hi> year, but onely endeavour to make it certain, that on this day of that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth <hi>December</hi> that Feaſt hath ever been ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the Weſtern Church; from whence the Eaſtern alſo anciently received it. For it is clear, that upon what day ſoever of any Moneth an unmoveable feaſt is to be kept in our <hi>Iulian</hi> year, on the ſame day of the Month it is to be kept in the <hi>Gregorian;</hi> ſo that the proof here is equal for the uſe of both Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts. Thus appears the ſtate of the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion; and to this purpoſe, for orders ſake, ſhall be ſhewed,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Authorities of keeping it on this day both in the Eaſtern and Weſtern Churches, about</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:115666:8"/>400. <hi>years after our Saviour, and that then it was ancient in the Weſtern Church, and known alſo under the name of the Winter-Solſtice-day; which is eſpecially here obſervable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>For preparation of more particular proof of the tradition of this Feaſt-day, the ſuppoſition which the moſt primitive Ages had touching the time of the Solſtices and Aequinoxes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That the keeping of it on this day was ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from tradition, even of the eldeſt times ſince our Saviour; and this juſtified from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſuppoſing it to have been upon the very day of the ancient Winter-Solſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Expreſs Teſtimonies to the ſame purpoſe out of ancient Hiſtory, and a confirmation from the general uſe in the ſeveral Churches in Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>The chief Objections that are made againſt this dayes being the true time of the birth, with plain Anſwers to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Some other Opinions among the Ancients touching it, and how ſome of them may agree with what we have received, and the reſt are of no weight againſt it: And then more eſpecially of the ancient confuſion of this Feaſt with that of the Epiphany.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:115666:8"/>
               <head>SECT. I. <hi>The Authorities of keeping it on this day both in the Eaſtern and Weſtern Churches about</hi> 400. <hi>years after our Saviour; and that then it was ancient in the Weſtern Church, and known alſo under the name of the Winter-Solſtice-day; which is especially here obſervable.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOr the firſt, that is, the Authorities of the received uſe of keeping this Feaſt on the 25 of <hi>December</hi> 400 years after Chriſts Birth, they are frequent in S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> S. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome,</hi> S. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> and others of the Fathers that liv'd about the end of thoſe 400 years: Thoſe three eſpecially have many Sermons appropriated to the celebration of this day, and they frequently tell the people confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently, that the Birth of our Saviour was on the 25 of <hi>December,</hi> or the 8 Kalends of <hi>January;</hi> as alſo that the birth of Saint <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> was on the 8 Kalends of <hi>July,</hi> or the 24 day of <hi>June,</hi> according as to this day they are obſerved. <hi>Ecce,</hi> ſaith
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Serm. de Temp.</hi> 8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.</note> Saint <hi>Ambroſe, in nativitate Chriſti dies creſcit, &amp; Johannis nativi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate decreſcit; illo oriente lux proficit, hoc naſcente minuitur:</hi> That is, On our Saviours Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day the days begin to lengthen, and on St. <hi>Johns</hi> to ſhorten; for the Fathers herein ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the 25 of <hi>December</hi> to be the Winter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at what time ever the days begin to lengthen; and the 24 of <hi>June</hi> to be the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer-ſolſtice,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115666:9"/>in which they contrariwiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to ſhorten: and this was according to the ancienter Aſtronomy, out of which ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this Feaſt-day, the antiquity of the tradition ſhall be alſo preſently confirmed. And to this purpoſe of the Summer-ſolſtice at St <hi>Johns</hi> Birth, and of the Winter at our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours, they apply (I diſpute not how well) that in St. <hi>John,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>D. Joan. c.</hi> 3. <hi>comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n.</hi> 30.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, i. He muſt increaſe, but I muſt be diminiſhed. So St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> alſo, <hi>Natus
<note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>D. Aug. ſerm. ded verſis</hi> 40. <hi>&amp;</hi> 59. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ. Creſcon. c.</hi> 37. <hi>&amp; in Pſalm.</hi> 132.</note> eſt Johannes hodiè, ab hodierno minuuntur dies; na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt Chriſtus</hi> 8 <hi>Kalend. Januarias, ab illo die creſcunt dies.</hi> And enough to this purpoſe oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curs in others of that
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>D. Hiero. in epiſt. de celebr. Paſch. tom.</hi> 4.</note> age, wherein theſe two Births were obſerved, and only theſe two, and that in all, or the greateſt part of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom; <hi>Solius Domini</hi> (ſaith
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Serm. de fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis</hi> 2.</note> St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) <hi>&amp; Beati Iohannis dies Nativitatis in univerſo mundo celebratur &amp; colitur.</hi> But it being clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly plain that about this time of 400 years paſt after our Saviour, this 25 day was ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, and taken generally for his Birth-day, it falls next to inquire the original whence it was ſo taken: Had thoſe <hi>Clementines</hi> been of ſufficient credit, there had been no need to have made any further inquiry; for then we might have thence reſolved that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles had ordained it; and it had been fit for them that ſtand ſo much for the Authority of thoſe Conſtitutions, to have proved that the Apoſtles had done ſo, that ſo they might
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115666:9"/>have cleared that ſuppoſititious Volume of ſuch a Character of falſhood. For doubtleſs had ſuch a Conſtitution been publiſhed in that Volume, and by the Apoſtles, the Eaſtern Church had not ſo long been ignorant of it, as it appears by St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> they were: For untill ſome 10 years before his Sermon
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>D. Chryſ. edit. Savilianâ, tom.</hi> 5: {fo. <hi>p.</hi> 511.</note> made upon this day, eſpecially for the truth of the time of the Feaſt, that Church had not been generally inſtructed with this certainty of it; for then it was newly learn'd from the Weſtern Church, in which even from <hi>Thrace</hi> to <hi>Cadiz</hi> (as he tells us from ſuch as inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him) it was ſo obſerv'd. But although that Ordinance touching it in the <hi>Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines,</hi> attributed to the Apoſtles, be ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titious, yet there is great reaſon for us to think that the tradition of this Feaſt to be ſo kept on that day was Apoſtolical, that is, taught and deduced into the Church (though not in writing) both from the Apoſtles, and firſt Diſciples and Obſervers of our Saviour. <hi>Quid autem</hi> (ſaith
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Adverſ. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Irenaeus</hi>) <hi>ſi neque Apoſtoli quidem ſcripturas reliquiſſent nobis, nonne oporte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat ordinem ſequi traditionis quam tradiderunt iis quibus committebant Eccleſias?</hi> And we ſhall here uſe aptly enough the very words alſo of <hi>Tertul.</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>De corona mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litis c.</hi> 4.</note> ſpeaking of divers obſervations in both Sacraments, and other parts of Chriſtian Religion in his time, which was near the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles; <hi>Harum &amp; aliarum ejuſmodi Diſcipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narum ſi legem expoſtules ſcripturarum, nullam
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115666:10"/>invenies:</hi> But, <hi>traditio praetendetur auctrix, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudo confirmatrix, &amp; fides obſervatrix.</hi> But for the order of proof here (it being firſt cleared that this tradition was about the time of thoſe Fathers that teſtifie it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly received in Chriſtendom) before we come to the particular deductions of it out of the elder ages that preceded them, we ſhall here not untimely firſt note, that as it was commonly received as a thing then ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, ſo was it generally thought of as what was then very ancient. So ſaies St. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom</hi> expreſly,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Serm. dict. item in hom.</hi> 34. <hi>tom.</hi> 2. <hi>edit. Baſil. &amp; in ſerm.</hi> 27. <hi>de nat. Jo. Baptiſt. co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem tom.</hi>
                  </note> being inſtructed from learned men of the Weſtern Church, it was then <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, of ancient time, and delivered in the Church many years before, as his words are; and yet, ſaith he, it is new too, new in the Eaſtern Church, becauſe (as he writes) we have ſo lately learn'd it, that is, within ten years ſince; but he calls it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> i. old and very ancient, in that it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of equal age with the ancienter feaſt-dayes which they had received: and again, though it came but lately into the Eaſtern Church, yet it was, ſaith he, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, i. well known from ancient time to thoſe that were of the Weſtern Church. And St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> alſo
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Enarrat. in Pſalm.</hi> 132.</note> expreſly ſayes that the birth was up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this day, <hi>ſic tradit Eccleſia;</hi> which denotes
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115666:10"/>great antiquity even in his time: and in
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Serm. de ſanct.</hi> 4.</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother place ſpeaking of the celebration of St. <hi>Iohn Baptiſts</hi> birth-day, which was recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with this, it ſeems, by a like tradition, <hi>Hoc majorum traditione ſuſcepimus,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hoc ad poſteros imitanda devotione tranſmittimus.</hi> Theſe paſſages alone are enough teſtimony that this Feaſt-day thus placed was reputed in thoſe times, that is, about 400. years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt, very ancient: But to know how ancient it was more particularly, it behoves us to look backward from thoſe times by ſuch degrees, as that by careful obſerving one of them after another, up towards the times of our Saviour, we may be herein in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed according to the occurrence of ſuch teſtimony as may make to the end of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry; and I doubt not but we ſhall ſo well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough at length find it receiv'd in the Church, in the Weſtern Church, even from Apoſtolical tradition, deriv'd from obſervation, while yet our Saviour was on the earth. But to begin this courſe of inquiry by looking back by degrees from the time of St. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> and the reſt of the Fathers of about his age, we ſhall firſt look on the time of near 100. years before them, that is, of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, and the firſt general Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> held in the year 325. at which time we ſhall with ſufficient arguments firſt ſhew, that this Feaſt was kept on the 25. of <hi>December,</hi> as now it is, and that then alſo from ancienter
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115666:11"/>time; againſt thoſe which ſuppoſe the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of it no elder than after or about <hi>Conſtantine:</hi> And from thence we ſhall go upward to the Apoſtles. But becauſe that hath firſt reference to the time of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, and makes much otherwiſe alſo for confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the antiquity of this, and the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of the day (as ſhall be preſently ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) conſiſts eſpecially in obſervation of the name of the time under which thoſe Fathers received, denoted and celebrated it, that is, of the very day of the Winter-Solſtice, with reference to the Spring-Aequinox, as to the time of the conception of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and to the Summer-Solſtice, and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumn-Aequinox, as to St. <hi>Iohns</hi> birth and conception; it is firſt here requiſite that we ſhortly open the ancient ſuppoſition which the moſt primitive times had touching thoſe four beginings of the Quarters of the year, which (being much different from what was received, both at the time of the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> and before it, and ſomewhat is alſo yet retain'd in Church-cycles) will make way for confirmation of the receiv'd opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that ſacred Birth-day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:115666:11"/>
               <head>SECT. II. <hi>For preparation of more particular proof of the Tradition of this Feaſt-day, the ſuppoſition which the moſt Primitive Ages had touching the time of the Solſtices and Aequinoxes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe ancient and civil ſuppoſition of the Solſtices and Aequinoxes, (in which an expreſs character is found of the Antiquity of this Tradition, as ſhall be preſently ſhewed) was both before and about our Saviours Birth-day, (eſpecially in the Roman Empire) of another kind from that which either at this day is, or at the time of the Birth was agreeable to the more accurate and naturall Aſtronomy; I mean, the ſuppoſition which was generally received in their Characters and <hi>Parapegmata,</hi> which denoted both their Sacrifices, Feaſt-days, and Country-obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for matter of Husbandry: For they ſuppoſed in thoſe Calendars, that the Suns entrance into the 1 degree of <hi>Aries</hi> was on the 15 Kalends of <hi>April</hi> in the <hi>Julian</hi> year, that is, on the 18 day of <hi>March;</hi> but that the ſpring-aequinox was not untill the 8 Kalends of <hi>April,</hi> that is, the 17 of <hi>June,</hi> they placed the Suns firſt entrance into <hi>Cancer;</hi> but the Solſtice on 8 Kalends, that is, on the 24 of <hi>June.</hi> So the 15 Kalends of <hi>October,</hi> or the 17 of <hi>September,</hi> was their ſuppoſed time of the Suns firſt entrance into <hi>Libra;</hi> but the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115666:12"/>Autumn-aequinox on the 8 Kalends, or the 24 of <hi>September;</hi> and according to theſe the firſt entrance of the Sun into <hi>Capricorn</hi> they placed on the 15 Kalends of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> or the 18 of <hi>December:</hi> So that the Aequinoxes and Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices were not ſuppoſed in the firſt entrance, or in the 1 degree of thoſe 4 ſignes (as at this day they are, and many ages ſince have been) but at ſuch time as the Sun held the 8 degrees of them. For the Suns proper Diurnal motion being about a degree, it ſo fell out in their Calculation, that 8 days being reckon'd from the firſt entrance into every of thoſe ſigns (as is ſeen in the examples) on the 8 day the Sun was in the 8 degrees of thoſe ſignes, and then made the ſuppoſed time of Solſtices and Aequinoxes. The teſtimonies of this kind of placing in thoſe times are frequent. <hi>Ovid</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Faſtorum l.</hi> 6.</note> expreſly teacheth us ſo for the Summer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolſtice. But in the Calendar that is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly joyned with him, and received by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, it is therein miſtaken. The like for all four do <hi>Pliny,
<note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>Hiſt. nat. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 19. <hi>l.</hi> 18. <hi>c.</hi> 25. <hi>&amp;</hi> 29.</note> Columel,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>De re Ruſticâ c.</hi> 14. <hi>&amp; l.</hi> 11. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> Vitruvius,
<note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>Architect. l.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> Martia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Capella</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Nupt. Philol. &amp; Mercur.</note>, the Scholiaſt on <hi>Germanicus</hi> his <hi>Aratus,</hi> and the Author of the fragment joyn'd with <hi>Cenſorinus:</hi> And of the naturall forces of the two Tropiques or Solſtices, to this purpoſe <hi>Manilius;</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Aſtron. l.</hi> 3. <hi>ad extrem.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <q>
                     <l>Has quidam vires octavâ in parte reponunt;</l>
                     <l>Sunt quibus eſſe placet decimas; nec defuit Autor</l>
                     <l>Qui primae momenta daret, fraenosque dierum.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:115666:12"/>
               <p>Meaning that the common opinion was, they were (with the Aequinoxes) in the eight part of their ſigns, but that ſome thought them otherwiſe; ſome in the tenth, ſome (as they ought) in the firſt. But this opinion of the eight parts, and ſo by conſequence of thoſe times of the Aequinoxes and Solſtices was a moſt ancient tradition, and retained ſtill in their Calendars, or <hi>Faſti,</hi> made for ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, ſacred and ruſtick uſe; notwithſtanding that the more accurate Aſtronomers had found it to be an errour; not otherwiſe then at this day thoſe which keep the <hi>Iulian</hi> and <hi>Dionyſian</hi> account in the Church, (as we in <hi>Great Britain</hi>) ſuppoſe the ſpring-aequinox on the 21 of <hi>March,</hi> though the known A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtronomy teach us that it anticipates about 11 days. And as it happens in like caſes, they ſtill retain'd what had been from anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent time ſetled in the State, neglecting the corrected Aſtronomy; and that eſpecially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thoſe old Calendars were already fitted to their Feaſts and Sacrifices, and were more known to the people, who could not but have been much troubled with an innovation of the time of all their publick ſolemnities. Neither <hi>Soſigenes</hi> in his divers amendments of the year made upon <hi>Iulius Caeſars</hi> commands, or the reſt after him ſo imployed, alter any thing in this ſuppoſition: All which is fully expreſſed in that of <hi>Columella,</hi> in his Precepts of Husbandry; where having firſt ſpoken of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115666:13"/>the Solſtices and Aequinoxes, falling upon the 8 degrees of thoſe ſignes, he preſently thus admoniſhes:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Agricult.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> c. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Nec me fallit</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Hipparchi ratio, quae docet Solſtitia &amp; Aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctia non octavis, ſed primis partibus ſignorum confici: Verum in hac ruris diſciplina ſequor Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxi &amp; Metonis, antiquorumque faſtos Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logorum, qui ſunt aptati publicis ſacrificiis; quia &amp; notior eſt iſta velus Agricolis concepta opinio.</hi> He gives here the true reaſon why that ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition was retained; but, by the way, is deceived in this, that he takes <hi>Eudoxus</hi> and <hi>Meton</hi> to be of thoſe ancienter Aſtronomers from whom it was received. It is true indeed that in the old
<note n="†" place="margin">Parap. quod gemino ſubne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitur.</note> 
                  <hi>Parapegmata,</hi> which ſhew us that according to. <hi>Calippus</hi> and <hi>Euctemon,</hi> the Solſtices and Aequinoxes were at the firſt entrance of the Sun into the ſignes proper for them: <hi>Eudoxus</hi> yet had otherwiſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced them; as for the purpoſe, the ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aequinox on the 6 day after the Suns entrance into <hi>Aries,</hi> and the Winter-ſolſtice on the 4 day after the 1 entrance into <hi>Capricorn:</hi> But we find not that he had taught this learning of the 8 days or parts; no more do we that <hi>Meton</hi> was any teacher of it; although alſo for this particular, beſide the publiſhed <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rapegmata,</hi> I made ſpeciall ſearch alſo for it in <hi>Ptolomies</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cod. Ms. eſt</hi> V. C. <hi>Henrici Savill Eq. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rati; mihi verè communicavit pro ſuâ huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate</hi> V. C. <hi>T. Bambridge Medicinae D &amp; Mathematicus egregius.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a Book never yet printed, but fraught with divers pieces of the <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pegmata</hi> both of <hi>Meton</hi> and <hi>Eudoxus;</hi> and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115666:13"/>wholly another thing from that which goes under a like name for <hi>Ptolomies,</hi> publiſhed at the end of ſome Editions of <hi>Ovids Faſti.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, it is certain that the Summer-Solſtice obſerved by <hi>Meton</hi> with <hi>Euctemon</hi> in the 316. year of <hi>Nabonaſſar,</hi> that is about CCCCXL. before Chriſt, was upon the 21. of the <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> Moneth <hi>Phamenoth,</hi> as
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mathemat. Syntax. l.</hi> 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Ptolomy</hi> expre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly teſtifies, which for that time agrees with the 27. of the <hi>Iulian Iune.</hi> Neither <hi>Eudoxus</hi> therefore, nor <hi>Meton,</hi> thus placed the Solſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces on the 8. Kalends of their Moneths. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of late time have much troubled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to find the ground or original whence this ſuppoſition came among the Ancients; as eſpecially Cardinal <hi>Contaren, Geneſius de Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulveda,</hi> and moſt of all <hi>Joſeph Scaliger;</hi> but their conjectures are moſt uncertain, and too weak to rely on. Neither, I gueſs, will the original be found among any of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients that are claſſick in Authority, but in a Tranſcript of ſome parts of a Latine Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation by <hi>Abraham de Balmis,</hi> of a Book tit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Copiam mihi perhumaniter fecit v. c.</hi> Jac. Uſherus, <hi>ſacrae Theol. D. undi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> doctiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Iſagogicon Aſtrologiae Ptolomaei,</hi> (which indeed appears to be <hi>Geminus Phaenomena</hi>) compar'd with the Greek; I find theſe words, as if they were but tranſlated from the firſt Author, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>terque Tropicus, &amp; ambo Aequinoxia, ſecundum Astrologorum Graeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum opinionem, fiunt in primis gradibus horum Signorum; ſed ſecundum Chaldaeorum opinio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, in octavis gradibus:</hi> but the Greek copy
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115666:14"/>had no ſuch thing; though it be like enough that the copy whence he tranſlated it had, that is an Arabick copy of <hi>Geminus,</hi> who, as <hi>Euclide</hi> alſo, <hi>Ptolomy, Ariſtotle,</hi> much of <hi>Galen,</hi> and other Greek Authors, was turned out of Greek into Arabick, and thence into Latine, long before the Greek it ſelf was tranſlated immediately into Latine, as we have it at this day: and it appears that his tranſlation was from an Arabick copy, in that alone, that the <hi>parapegma</hi> which is at the end of this Latine <hi>Geminus,</hi> hath the names of <hi>Eudoxus, Calippus, Euctemon, Dolitheus</hi> and <hi>Meton,</hi> ſo varied as frequently other names are, which are expreſſed out of Arabick letters into La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin in like tranſlations; as for <hi>Eudoxus,</hi> it hath <hi>Orchalis;</hi> for <hi>Calippus, Philidis;</hi> for <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctemon, Octiman;</hi> for the other two, <hi>Duſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> and <hi>Matheon;</hi> all which plainly miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the tranſlator, when he found either the names written without eſſential points in the Arabick character, or elſe miſ-tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, as it might eaſily be, by ſuch a wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that was not worthy to be truſted to; for the miſhaping of a letter, or the doubling of a point, and the like, ſoon makes ſuch va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riance of names expreſſed out of that Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. But for the matter of the 8 degrees, and the Solſtices and Aequinoxes referred to them, here is authority that it had original from
<note n="*" place="margin">9 <hi>Kal. Jan. Brumale ſolſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium obſervant</hi> Chaldaei, <hi>ait</hi> Columella, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. l. 11. c. 2.</note> the <hi>Chaldees,</hi> which I yet think is as far from truth as that of <hi>Columel's;</hi> neither is
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115666:14"/>this a fit place to make larger inquiry after it. It here ſufficeth to ſhew it manifeſt, that this placing of thoſe parts of the year was obſerved from anicnet time, and that eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the State of <hi>Rome;</hi> as we ſee alſo in thoſe their old Country-Feaſts, the <hi>Robega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> the <hi>Floralia,</hi> the <hi>Vinalia;</hi> which were the three main Feaſts wherein from ancient time they made interceſſion to their gods a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all hurt that might happen to their green Corn, and the ripening of the fruits, and their Vintage; and were kept and ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by * <hi>Varro,</hi> according to another account of the Suns place or motion then is before delivered. And according to this account are the Aequinoxes and Solſtices in Venerable <hi>Bede's</hi> Ephemeris, noted with the addition of <hi>juxta quoſdam</hi> to be underſtood, although in the Print they ſomewhat vary it: but it is clear, that in his <hi>December</hi> the <hi>Solſtitium juxta quoſdam,</hi> and in his <hi>March</hi> the <hi>Aequinoctium juxta quoſdam,</hi> are both placed a day before they ſhould be, that is, they ought to be on the 8. Calends, (not the 9.) the one of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> the other of <hi>April;</hi> with which the <hi>Sol</hi> in <hi>Capri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corn,</hi> and the <hi>Sol</hi> in <hi>Aries,</hi> there before no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to the 15. Calends, exactly ſuppoſe the Solſtice in the 8. degree of <hi>Capricorn,</hi> and the <hi>Aequinox</hi> in the 8. of <hi>Aries,</hi> that is, in the 25. dayes of their Moneths; reference being ſtill had to this ancient account, which he, being moſt curious in the cycles of time,
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Apud Plin. l.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 19. <hi>&amp; Scholiaeſt. ad Aratea prognoſtica.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:115666:15"/>would not omit; although his <hi>Ephemeris</hi> were purpoſely made for the <hi>Dionyſian</hi> year, which alſo he hath together expreſſed in the ſame colums: But, I ſuppoſe, the chief reaſon why theſe two ſtand ſo diſplaced, is, becauſe the noting of the birth of St. <hi>Anaſtaſia</hi> was thought more neceſſary to the 8. Cal. of <hi>Ian.</hi> than this old ſuppoſed Solſtice to be added, it was caſt upon a void place of a line next pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding. The ſame may be ſaid of the Spring-aequinox, which had no room on the 8 Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lend of <hi>April</hi> in the Column, by reaſon of the conception and paſſion of our Saviour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether noted to that day; and that he is ſo to be underſtood, he himſelf elſewhere is
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>De Temb. ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione, c.</hi> 28.</note> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony enough, expreſly relating this ancient courſe of accounting the Solſtices and Aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxes: So that his <hi>Ephemeris</hi> is a ſpecial ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of it, if rightly underſtood; as alſo is that <hi>Calendarium Romanum,</hi> lately cut in Braſs, and ſo publiſhed from the print, as ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be as ancient as <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great; where the Summer-ſolſtice is indeed by the cutters or tranſcribers fault ſet to the 7 Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lend of <hi>Iuly,</hi> which plainly ſhould have been on the eighth, and the Suns entrance into <hi>Cancer</hi> is on the 17 Kalend which ſhould be on the 15, as alſo the Suns entrance into <hi>Aries</hi> ſhould have been placed on the 15 Kalend of <hi>April,</hi> which agrees juſt with the Feaſt of <hi>Hilaria</hi> being on the 8 Kalend. And accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this ſuppoſition of the ancients, did
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115666:15"/>that learned Gentleman, <hi>George Herwart van Hochenburg,</hi> (out of whoſe Library this Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendar was lately publiſhed) judiciouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the reaſon of thoſe differences that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in it from the later Aſtronomy; and in his Letter written to Seignior <hi>Haleander,</hi> a Gentleman of curious learning in <hi>Rome,</hi> the Copy whereof was thence ſent me through the hand of that learned and worthy Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Monſieur <hi>Piereſe,</hi> an Advocate in the Parliament of <hi>Aix;</hi> and this ſome two years ſince, when 'twixt him and my ſelf, and from him to <hi>Haleander</hi> divers Letters paſſed touching the particulars and authority of that Calendar.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>SECT. III. <hi>That the keeping of it this day was ſo receiv'd from tradition, even of the eldeſt times ſince our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; and this juſtified from the Fathers, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing it to have been on the very day of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Winter-ſolſtice.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat ancient ſuppoſition of the Solſtices and Aequinoxes being thus hitherto firſt opened, let us in looking back by degrees, firſt (as is before propoſed) begin with the time of the Councel of <hi>Nice,</hi> held in the year of our Saviour 325. It will ſo appear, that before that Council, this Feaſt was eſtabliſhed in the Weſtern Church, and that by the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115666:16"/>teſtimony of thoſe Fathers, which with one voice ſuppoſe it as formerly placed on the very day of the Winter-ſolſtice; for had it been begun after or about the time of that Council, and withall ſuppoſed to have ought to have been kept on the Winter-ſolſtice day, then doubtleſs would they have placed it on that day which was received in the Church to be the Winter-ſolſtice-day, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or about the ſame Council, as at this day in the <hi>Gregorian</hi> year, who doubts but that a Feaſt to be newly inſtituted on an Aequinox or Solſtice, or with reference to either of thoſe times, would be placed by them which have received that Reformation on the Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoxes or Solſtices, or with reference to them according as they are in the corrected Calendar, and not as they fall in the <hi>Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ian</hi> or <hi>Dionyſian</hi> year? For example alſo, what greater teſtimony were there (if all other were loſt) to prove the antiquity of that very kind of keeping the Feaſt of <hi>Eaſter</hi> as we do in our Church, to be of the Primitive time, than this, that the <hi>Paſchales termini</hi> are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd ſtill according to the Spring-aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nox receiv'd in the Primitive times? Now to make clear our purpoſe, here it is alſo certain that about and after that Councel of <hi>Nice,</hi> the Spring-oequinox according whereunto the Paſchal-cycles were made, was ſuppoſed in the Church upon the 21 of <hi>March,</hi> as it is ſeen alſo in the Paſchal-account uſed to this
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115666:16"/>day in the Church of <hi>England;</hi> ſo that it was become four dayes ſooner than in thoſe elder times, when it fell in common opinion on the 25 day: but when the Spring-aequinox was ſo changed, and according to the change alſo received, it could not but follow that the beginning of the other three parts of the year muſt alſo be altered, that is plainly ſeen in the known courſe of the Suns motion. And therefore the Solſtices and the other Aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxes muſt alſo vary in their moneths, and by a like or very
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide ſis Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel. Francolin. de temp. hor. ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonic. c.</hi> 75 <hi>&amp;</hi> 76.</note> near like difference of days anticipate, as they are accordingly cited in <hi>Bede's Ephemeris,</hi> who
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>De temp. Nat. c.</hi> 28.</note> elſewhere alſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhes us as much. Therefore it muſt follow too, that about and after that gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councel the time of the Winter-ſolſtice was placed (and ſo ſuppoſed in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical account) upon the 21 or 22 of <hi>December.</hi> But if it had been ſo receiv'd when this Feaſt-day was firſt ordained, and ſpecially placed on the Solſtice-day (as the Fathers generally by tradition from former times place it) there had been neceſſary cauſe enough to have had it fallen yearly three or four days ſooner than it did, both in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times and at this day, that is, on the 21 or 22 of the ſame moneth. By conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence it was then ordained or receiv'd in the Church, at ſuch time as the Winter-ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice was not ſuppoſed on the 21 or 22 day of the ſame moneth, but on the 25, that is, at
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115666:17"/>leaſt before that Councel of <hi>Nice,</hi> or <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> the Great, howſoever too raſhly ſome have delivered
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Joſ. Scal. de emendat. Temp. l.</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 510. <hi>&amp; Calviſius Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gog. chron. c.</hi> 46.</note> of it, that <hi>poſt ſeculum Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantim Romae haec obſervatio inſtituta eſt.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can Objection have power here, which perhaps may obviouſly be brought to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne this kind of argument; that is, that it might notwithſtanding be ordained firſt in the later part of the primitive times, or after <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> or that Council, in ſuch ſort that it might be placed on the day of the Solſtice that was received at the time of the birth, that is, the 25. day, and not that which the received account had ſo innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: for this Objection is partly anſwered before in the paſſage of Feaſts at this day to be ordain'd, with reference to the Solſtices in the <hi>Gregorian</hi> Calendar: and beſides, if the Church about this time after <hi>Conſtantine</hi> had regarded in a new Inſtitution the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the time of the birth, according as it was then to be found in the Moneth, it muſt be that they either regarded the true and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, or the receiv'd and civil Solſtice. For the firſt, if they had been ſo curious as to have ſought what the true place of the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſolſtice to this purpoſe had been in the age of that birth, as they had indeed ſought for the true Aequinox of their own time for their direction of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> they had found that the true Solſtice anticipated the 25. day about two dayes; for, by the moſt accurate
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115666:17"/>calcularion to the noon of the Meridian of <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> on the 25. of <hi>December,</hi> in the year commonly attributed to the birth of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, the Sun was in the ſecond degree of <hi>Capricorn,</hi> and ſome minutes over, as
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Comment. ad Ptolem. qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dripartit. l.</hi> 2. <hi>com.</hi> 54. <hi>&amp; Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ſis Clavium ad cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Joh. de Sacro boſco. Alter quidem Colurus, p.</hi> 297. <hi>edit.</hi> 4. 1602.</note> 
                  <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan</hi> alſo places it in the ſcheme of that nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity; whence it muſt clearly follow, that about the 23. day was the very point of the Winter-ſolſtice, the diurnal true motion of that time of the year in the <hi>Perigaeum</hi> being ſomewhat more than a degree. No place was then for this true Solſtice in ſuch their conſideration of the birth-time, if they had thus inquired after it, unleſs they would have inſtituted the Feaſt (under that name of time) on the 23. day, and not on the 25. For the ſecond, what colour have we to think that they ſhould in thoſe times have retain'd the old ſuppoſition of the civil Solſtice for their Inſtitution of this Feaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, and yet ſo carefully alter the formerly-received aequinox for <hi>Eaſter?</hi> This of the birth being as the head and rule of the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt immoveable Feaſts, as that of the Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Reſurrection is of the moveable. Would they have retained the ſame error upon Inſtitution of a new Feaſt, which with ſo much curioſity they corrected in eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing the certainty of an old one? It reſts firme therefore, that whenſoever it was firſt inſtituted for anniverſary celebration, it was in ſuch an Age as had the ſuppoſition of the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115666:18"/>Winter-ſolſtice being on the 25. day of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember</hi> yet retain'd in the Church; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe what dependence were there 'twixt the name of the Feaſt and the Solſtice? But that dependence is by the conſent of the Fathers fully teſtified, as a tradition of former times; and the lateſt Age which in the Church re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd that ſuppoſition, muſt at leaſt be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> as is already ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; therefore at leaſt the Inſtitution of it muſt precede that Council.</p>
               <p>This being hitherto deduced, it will in the next degree of ſearching backward fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low alſo, if we can prove the received ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the Church touching the time of the Winter-ſolſtice to have been long before this Council, agreeable to that which here is ſhewed to the time of it, that the firſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation or Inſtitution of this Feaſt, under the name of the Solſtice upon the 25. day, was alſo long before that Council. Now as the Spring-aequinox changed from the 25. to the 21. ſo did the Winter-ſolſtice of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity change alſo, as is before ſhewed: But the Spring-aequinox was alſo at leaſt ſome 50. years before that Council, upon the 21. or 22. of <hi>March,</hi> by the received ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them from whoſe direction the Church-cycles were principally guided, that is, of the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> and eſpecially thoſe of <hi>Alexandria;</hi> ſo is the expreſs
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Apud Euſeb. hiſt. eccleſ. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 26.</note> te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of <hi>Anatolius,</hi> born and bred in <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria,</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:115666:18"/>but Biſhop of <hi>Laodicea</hi> in the time of <hi>Aurelian,</hi> about 270 years after our Saviour. He ſhews that then the 11 Kalends of <hi>April,</hi> that is, the 22 of <hi>March</hi> was the ſuppoſed Aequinox; which agrees well enough with that of the 21, if regard be had to that varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which the houres out of which the Leap-year is made muſt of neceſſity be a cauſe of, as <hi>Bede</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>In epiſt. ad Wichred de Paſchatis cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, tom.</hi> 2.</note> withall in explanation of <hi>Anatolius</hi> hath taught us: The ſame <hi>Bede</hi> well admoniſhing, that it was <hi>Regula Niceno pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bato Concilio,</hi> not <hi>ſtatuta,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Wilfrid apud Bedam, hiſt. Angl. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 25.</note> to have that time receiv'd for the Spring-aequinox. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the very words of the Epiſtles ſent out of that Council touching it, and the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories plainly prove it to have been gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally known and receiv'd in the Church, both of the Weſt, North, South, and part of the Eaſt long before. In <hi>Conſtantines</hi> Epiſtle
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſeb. de vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Conſtant. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 18. <hi>Socrat. hiſt. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 21. <hi>Nicephor. l.</hi> 12. <hi>c.</hi> 33.</note> to the Churches of Chriſtendom ſent preſently upon the Council, it is expreſſed that it was ſo generally received before; and <hi>Ruffinus</hi> ſpeaking of the Council, tells us, that,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hiſt. eccleſ. l.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>De ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervatione Paſchae, antiquum Canonem, per quem nulla de reliquo varietas oriretur, tradiderunt.</hi> Nothing therefore can be clearer then that the aequinox of the 21 or 22 of <hi>March,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the difference before noted, was ancient in the traditions of the Church, long before the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council: Otherwiſe they had as well in expreſſe terms innovated the aequinox, as eſtabliſhed uniformity in obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115666:19"/>their <hi>Eaſter</hi> by it. Therefore alſo was the Winter-ſolſtice about the 21 or 22 of <hi>December</hi> in the traditions of the Church long before that Council then: what follows hence touching the inſtitution of the Feaſt which we inquire after, is according to the former inferences moſt apparent, for ſo much time as thoſe teſtimonies reach back unto.</p>
               <p>To go farther up in a third degree, it will be alſo juſtified, that the Aequinox, and by conſequence another Winter-ſolſtice then that of the 25 day of <hi>December,</hi> was not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ancienter then the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council in the Church-cycles, but alſo equal to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles times. For although we find in the Church-ſtory great differences of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive times touching the keeping of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> and divers cycles and Canons made for it, yet thoſe differences are chiefly about the day of the week whereon it ſhould be kept, as between the <hi>Teſſareskaidecatoi</hi> and the Churches of the Weſt, but never (in any te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of credit) about the diverſity of ſuppoſition of the Aequinox that directs it, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than according to that in <hi>Anatolius,</hi> which ſtands with the received time of the 21 of <hi>March,</hi> as is already noted; I ſay in any teſtimony of credit, for under favour of the learned, I conceive not that attributed to <hi>Theophilus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Caeſaria,</hi> and publiſhed at the end of <hi>Bedes</hi> Epiſtle to
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tom</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 232 <hi>edit.</hi> Colon.</note> 
                  <hi>Wichred,</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:115666:19"/>where the 25 day is ſuppoſed for the Aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nox to be other then ſuppoſititious, the whole ſhape of it hath the Character of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeiting: But the Aequinox is ſtill (for ought appears) ſuppoſed the ſame in that Controverſie about <hi>Eaſter</hi> had under
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſeb. eccleſ. hiſt. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 22. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> Pope <hi>Victor</hi> about the year CXC. as it was in the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> and the ſame alſo before <hi>Victor,</hi> even up to the time of the Apoſtles. What elſe is denoted in that of <hi>Proterius,</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch of <hi>Alexandria</hi> to P. <hi>Leo</hi> the Firſt, where he tels
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Apud Bed. de temp. rat. c.</hi> 42. <hi>&amp; Vide ſis Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olfrid apud e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>und. hiſt. eccl. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 22.</note> him that St. <hi>Mark</hi> had taught the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> (according as he had learned from St. <hi>Peter</hi>) that <hi>Eaſter</hi> was to be obſerved after the XIV. moon of the firſt moneth, the firſt moneth here was known by the ſpring-ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinox, of which if they had not been agreed, as much trouble (or more) would have been in eſtabliſhing of that, as there was in clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what day of the week the ſacred Feaſt of <hi>Eaſter</hi> was to be kept on. The like is affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the Apoſtolical tradition of that uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form celebration of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> by <hi>Ceolfrid</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Naitan</hi> King of the <hi>Picts:</hi> And to confirm more fully that the obſervation of it eſtabliſhed by the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council was ſuch as had been even from the beginning of Chriſtianity, or the Apoſtles time, the very words of the Epiſtle ſent by that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil to the Churches of <hi>Aegypt</hi> and <hi>Africk</hi> are, that now the controverſie was ended touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Eaſter,</hi> and that thoſe of the Eaſtern
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115666:20"/>Church that had before followed the <hi>Iews</hi> in obſerving it on the XIV. Moon, did hold it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Socrat. biſt. eccleſ. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>i.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the <hi>Romans,</hi> to us, and to all you who from the beginning obſerve <hi>Eaſter</hi> as we do; or, <hi>Conſone cum Romanis, &amp; vobiſcum, &amp; cum omnibus ab initio Paſcha cuſtodientibus,</hi> as <hi>Caſſiodore</hi> anciently tranſlated it;
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hiſt. Tripart. l.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>c.</hi> 12.</note> which ſhews alſo that in <hi>Socrates</hi> he read <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, from the beginning, as ſome Copies are; and not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>i.e.</hi> from ancient time, as in others the reading is. It followes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that even from the beginning, that is, from the Apoſtles time, the ſame Spring-aequinox was receiv'd in the Church, that is, the 21 or 22 of <hi>March</hi> as was afterward; and that it was thence eſtabliſhed on the 21 by the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> and that by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, in thoſe times of the Apoſtles, the formerly-receiv'd aequinox was altered from the 25 to the 22 or 21; and ſo alſo (as of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity it followes) the Winter-ſolſtice from the 25 of <hi>December</hi> to near about the 21 or 22 of the ſame moneth. Whence alſo it is to be concluded, that this Feaſt day was receiv'd as to be kept on the 25 day even before the Apoſtles time, and that among the Diſciples of our Saviour, while he was yet on earth, that is, while in common reputation the 25. day of <hi>December</hi> was taken for the Winter-ſolſtice: Otherwiſe what colour were
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115666:20"/>there why the conſent of the Fathers ſhould denote it by that civil Winter-ſolſtice which was out of uſe in the Church, both in their time, and been ſo likewiſe from the times of the Apoſtles, that is, from ſome time after the Paſſion of our Saviour, before which there was no need at all (for the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhing of our <hi>Eaſter,</hi> which was to be ruled by the Spring-aequinox) to vary the placing of thoſe points of the Quarters of the year? But it being commonly received, out of the account and Kalendar of the Gentiles, that the 25. of <hi>December</hi> was the Solſtice, and that on the ſame day our Saviour was born, it grew familiar, it ſeems, and ſo was delivered down to thoſe Fathers, that the birth-day was on the very Winter-ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, which they ſo often inculcate: But the Apoſtles and Evangeliſts not being able per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps in the infancy of the Church to ſettle the anniverſary celebration of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> until about their later times, that is, about 100. years after this birth, carefully obſerved, and eſpecially St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Mark,</hi> where the natural aequinox was, according to which the Solſtices ever vary, and ſo found it in that time about the 22. or 21. of <hi>March,</hi> as by exact calculation it will happen, according to that before noted tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching <hi>Anatolius;</hi> and hence they delivered the knowledge of the change of thoſe Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the year to poſterity. But alſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115666:21"/>even from the very birth it ſelf the 25. day of <hi>December</hi> had been kept, or known for it, notwithſtanding that it was in vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar opinion conceived to have been on the day attributed to the civil Solſtice,
<note n="*" place="margin">In common reputation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Gentiles; yet would they not vary it from that day, becauſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it had no reference to the Solſtice.</note> which anticipated it three dayes, as is before ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but was proper to the 25. day of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember</hi> onely, as it was the 25. of that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth: Although thoſe Fathers, being none of the beſt Aſtronomers, thought ſtill howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Solſtice was altered in their times, that at the time of the birth the natural Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice had fallen on the 25. day, and then onely they ſo often note it, miſtaking vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar ſuppoſition delivered in the Kalendars of the Gentiles for exact calculation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>SECT. IV. <hi>Expreſſe teſtimonies to the ſame purpoſe out of ancient Hiſtory, and a Confirmation from the general uſe in the ſeverall Churches of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NEither is this antiquity of certainty only thus proved from the common joyning the Feaſt with the Winter-ſolſtice in the Fathers expreſſions of it, but alſo from expreſſe teſtimonies denoting as much in relations of the ancients. In which to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve firſt a like courſe, as before, in going upward from the time of thoſe Fathers to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115666:21"/>the Apoſtles, we find, that many years before the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> that is, under <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> this Feaſt was thus celebrated, and that in ſome part of the Eaſtern Church alſo; however that Church was not gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally inſtructed in it, till in St. <hi>Chryſoſtoms</hi> age; For in the Church-ſtory
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Nicephor. Caliſtus, l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 6.</note> it appears, that under that Emperour, <hi>Anthimus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Nicomedia,</hi> together with many thouſand Chriſtians, were aſſembled to keep that Feaſt-day; when as the Emperour, or his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Perſecutor <hi>Maximinus,</hi> commanded fire to be put to the Church wherein they were aſſembled, and that none of them ſhould eſcape that would not ſacrifice preſently to <hi>Iupiter Victor;</hi> whereupon they all willingly receiv'd the Crown of Martyrdom: and in the ancient Martyrology of <hi>Rome,</hi> the paſſion of thoſe Martyrs is placed on the 25 of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember</hi> in theſe words, <hi>Nicomediae paſſio mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum millium Martyrum, qui cum in Chriſti natali ad dominicum conveniſſent,</hi> &amp;c. which alſo for the time is juſtified by the Greek
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>ad</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Menologie,</hi> where the words <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. that is, <hi>Anthimus</hi> aſſembling in his Church a multitude of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians on the Feaſt-day of Chriſts Birth, kept the Feaſt with them, &amp;c. But indeed the Greek Church caſts this Feaſt of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs on the 28 of <hi>December,</hi> as they do alſo
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115666:22"/>upon other dayes the
<note n="*" place="margin">Menol. ad di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctos dies.</note> memories of St. <hi>Eugenia</hi> and St. <hi>Anaſtaſia</hi> (both which the Weſtern Churches retain with this Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day on the 25) the one on the 22, the other on the 24 day. But this was done by them only, becauſe the more ſingle honour might be given both to our Saviours Birth, and to thoſe other names, being ſo divided: <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſolennitatem</hi> (ſpeaking of thoſe Martyrs ſaith
<note n="†" place="margin">Old Marty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rol. 8 Kalend Jan.</note> 
                  <hi>Baronius</hi>) <hi>celebriùs agerent, cam tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulerunt.</hi> As alſo among the <hi>Iews</hi> a Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was often uſed of their feaſts from one day to another, that two Sabbaths or great Feaſts might not concur, as their
<note n="*" place="margin">Talmud. maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſec. Roſh. Haſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſana.</note> Doctors deliver. Hence then it is enough alſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, firſt, that by ancient teſtimony of the Monuments of the Church, this Feaſt was thus obſerved before <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> or that Council of <hi>Nice</hi> which was held many years after the death of <hi>Diocleſian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But alſo to look farther upon the times preceding this Martyrdom, we ſhall find good teſtimony that it was taught to poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to be kept ſo, even by the Apoſtles, who knew it as a clear certainty while our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our was yet on earth: For though they or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd it not in thoſe Conſtitutions falſly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to them, or in any other Writer, yet might they teach it as a tradition to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd ever to the Church, as they did the changing of the Sabbath from the ſeventh day to the firſt of the week; the ſolemn Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115666:22"/>of the Devil at Baptiſm; the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Eaſter</hi> on the Sun-day, or the like, <hi>quas ſine ullius Scripturae inſtrumento,</hi> as
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>De corona militis, c.</hi> 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſayes, <hi>ſolius traditionis titulo, exinde conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinis patrocinio, vindicamus.</hi> To this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, among St. <hi>Chryſoſtoms</hi> Works in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, one Homily is
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Edit. Baſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. tom.</hi> 2. <hi>hom.</hi> 39.</note> 
                  <hi>De Nativitate Domim,</hi> as the Latine title is, for the Greek of that Homily I have not yet ſeen; wherein he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently, as elſewhere, teaches, that this day of <hi>December</hi> is the juſt day of that birth, and for his authority brings no leſs than St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> teſtimony; <hi>Petrus,</hi> are the words, <hi>qui hic fuit cum Joh. qui hìc fuit cum Jac. nos in occidente docuit;</hi> which hath plain reference to that before noted out of his long Oration for the ſame matter, where he tells
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Edit. Savil: tom.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 512.</note> us alſo, that in the controverſies of thoſe times touching this Feaſt, ſuch as defended it as what ought to be kept on this day, juſtified that it was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, i. <hi>Very ancient and from old time known, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous from Thract to Cadis, that is in the whole Weſtern Church.</hi> To theſe may be added that of <hi>Euodius,</hi> whom <hi>Nicephoras</hi> calls the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor of the Apoſtles, and it is delivered
<note n="†" place="margin">Suid in verb. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> that it was ordained by St. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf in <hi>Antioch;</hi> that we may ſo diſtinguiſh him from that other <hi>Euodius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zalis</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cujus nomini aſcribuntur o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pera aliquot ad ſin tom.</hi> 10. <hi>D. Aug. ſubjunc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> edit. Lova<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſi.</hi>
                  </note> in St. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> time; he in an Epiſtle touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the times of the Paſſion of our Saviour,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115666:23"/>of St. <hi>Stephens</hi> Martyrdome, of the death of the bleſſed Virgin, and the like, ſayes expre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly of her, (as the Latine is in
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ. biſt. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Nicephorus,</hi> tranſlated by <hi>Langius,</hi> for neither have I the Greek of him) <hi>Peperit autem mundi ipſius lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem, annum agens quindecimum</hi> 25. <hi>die menſis Decembris.</hi> And likewiſe in an old Greek Author (the Book being written about the time of Pope <hi>Honorius</hi> the Firſt) in the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brary of St. <hi>Mark's</hi> in <hi>Florence,</hi> expreſs te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony is, <hi>Apoſtolos memoriae prodidiſſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum ex Virgine natum Bethlemae</hi> 25. <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bris,</hi> as <hi>Albertus Widemonſtadius</hi> of his own ſight witneſſeth in his Notes on that impious Book called <hi>Mahomets</hi> Divinity, and brings alſo <hi>Heſychius</hi> his authority to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. And to theſe may be added <hi>Cedren, Oroſius,</hi> and ſome ancient Manuſcripts <hi>Faſti</hi> cited by <hi>Cuſpinian</hi> upon <hi>Caſſiodore;</hi> and there is authority alſo,
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Catholicus Armeniorum in legatione ad Arvienios malè legitur</hi> 20 <hi>Dec. tam. in Biblioth. Patrum edit.</hi> Pariſ. <hi>tom.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 864. <hi>quam in edit.</hi> Colon. <hi>tom.</hi> 12. <hi>part.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 891. <hi>Nam Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce erat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>quod vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere eſt apud</hi> Joſ. Scalig. <hi>in Iſagog. chron. l.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 30.</note> that howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Epiphamus</hi> in his Works have another deſignation of the day of this birth, (as anon is ſhewed) yet out of the Monuments of the Jews he learned, and then taught, that this was the very day; which they ſay was juſtified alſo by ſome Writers brought to <hi>Rome</hi> from <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> by <hi>Titus;</hi> which alſo is ſtrengthened by that of St. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> when he ſayes
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tom.</hi> 5. <hi>eait.</hi> Savil. <hi>ſol.</hi> 12.</note> expreſly, that in publick Records kept at <hi>Rome</hi> in his age, the exact time of the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115666:23"/>deſcription under <hi>Quirinus,</hi> ſpoken of by St. <hi>Luke,</hi> (which could not but be a ſpecial character of the time of our Saviours birth) was expreſſed; and then he goes on, <hi>But what is this to us,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that neither are at Rome, nor have been there, that ſo we might be ſure of it? yet hearken,</hi> ſaith
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 513.</note> he, <hi>and doubt not; for we have received the day</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, i. <hi>from thoſe which accurately know theſe things, and dwell at Rome; And that they</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, i. <hi>having from ancient time and old tradition celebrated it, have now alſo ſent us the knowledge of it.</hi> This is likewiſe confirmed by an old barbarous Tranſlation of what was taken out of <hi>Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canus</hi> and <hi>Euſebius,</hi> and publiſhed in the noble <hi>Scaliger's Theſaurus Temporum,</hi> where the words are, <hi>Aug. &amp; Sylvano Coſſ Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus noſter Jeſus Chriſtus natus eſt ſub Auguſto</hi> 8. <hi>calendas Ianuarias:</hi> and then, <hi>In ipſa die in qua natus eſt paſtores viderunt ſtellam, Chuac</hi> 28. which ſhould rather be 29. for ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees the 25. of <hi>December</hi> to that of the <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian Choiac,</hi> which the Author means. And <hi>Prudentius</hi> upon the day, ſuppoſing the
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>In hymn. ad calend.</hi> 8 <hi>Jan.</hi>
                  </note> old tradition of the concurrence of the Solſtice with it,
<q>
                     <l>Quid eſt quod arctum circulum</l>
                     <l>Sol jam recurrens deſerit?</l>
                     <l>Chriſtusne terris naſcitur,</l>
                     <l>Qui lucis auget tramitem?</l>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:115666:24"/>
                     <l>Hic ille natalis dies,</l>
                     <l>Quo te Creator ard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us</l>
                     <l>Spiravit, &amp; limo indidit,</l>
                     <l>Sermone carnem glutinant.</l>
                  </q> And of later times the Authorities are infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite.</p>
               <p>Theſe teſtimonies being compared with the conſent of the Fathers, that about 400. years after Chriſt have written that it was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, as is already ſhewed; and being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the arguments made againſt the ſuppoſed later inſtitution of it, out of the place of the received Winter-ſolſtice, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough manifeſt the antiquity and certainty of this ancient Feaſt-day, according as we now obſerve it; and that even from the age wherein it firſt brought forth the redemption of Mankind. And to theſe we may adde the conſent of Chriſtian Churches ever ſince a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thoſe 400. years; for after that the Eaſtern or Greek Church of <hi>Aſia</hi> had learned the truth of it from the Weſtern, (as is deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered) this celebration of it yearly increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and grew ſtill more famous through Chriſtendom: ſo expreſly St. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſaith
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>g. in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> dit. Sav. l. to n.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 512.</note> he, i.e. <hi>Every year it increaſed and grew more famous.</hi> But indeed, becauſe in ſome places it was not as yet ſo received, but that old erroreous opinion touching it
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115666:24"/>(as it happens in like caſes, and ſhall anon be more particularly ſhewed) ſtill held there place among ſome that were too wayward to be brought to prefer truth newly diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to them before their own errors, therefore about 100. years after St. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome,</hi> it was expreſly ordained by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Iuſtin</hi> (if my Author deceive not) that in every place of the Chriſtian world it ſhould be thus obſerved: My Author here is <hi>Nicephorus
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Hiſt. eccleſ. l.</hi> 17. <hi>c.</hi> 28.</note> Caliſtus,</hi> who (as the Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of him is) tells us firſt of <hi>Iuſtinian,</hi> that he <hi>Primùm Servatoris exceptionem</hi> (that is, the <hi>Hypatants,</hi> which in our Weſtern Church is the Purification of the bleſſed Virgin) <hi>tot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> orbe terrarum feſto die honorare inſtituit:</hi> and then he addes, <hi>ſicut Iuſtinus de ſancta Chriſti nativitate fecit.</hi> And according hereto are the Kalendars and Book of Divine ſervice, not onely of the Weſtern, which are every where common, but of the Eaſtern Churches alſo: In the Menology of the Greek Church in <hi>December,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. i. <hi>On the</hi> 25. <hi>of the ſame moneth, the Feaſt of the Incarnation of our Lord, and God, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> and
<q>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</q> That is, <hi>The Virgin Mary brought forth our Saviour on the</hi> 25. <hi>day.</hi> Other Volumes of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115666:25"/>their Divine ſervice, as their <hi>Apoſtolo-Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gela,</hi> and the like, enough ſhew this alſo. And for other Churches which are not under the name of the Greek, as thoſe of <hi>Antioch,</hi> or <hi>Syriae,</hi> of <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> and of <hi>Elcopti</hi> or <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> although we have not their Calendars publiſhed with ſuch exactneſs of the placeing of their feaſts, as we have thoſe of the Greek Church, yet have we teſtimonies enough of them alſo, whence we may collect that they agree with us in this anniverſary cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration: As, firſt, for that of <hi>Antioch,</hi> they keep
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Wid monſtad. in epiſt. ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexâ Teſt. Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riac. &amp; vide ſis computum Antioch. a pud</hi> Joſ. Scalig. <hi>l.</hi> 7 <hi>de emendat. tomo p.</hi> 670.</note> this birth upon the ſame day with us in their Moneth <hi>Canun</hi> the former; and in <hi>Alfragan</hi> (as he is tranſlated) we read in his enumeration of the <hi>Syriack</hi> Moneths, <hi>Canun prior</hi> 31. <hi>dierum, cujus</hi> 25. <hi>nox vocatur nox Nativitatis:</hi> So in the <hi>Aethiopian</hi> Church on the 29. of their Moneth
<note n="†" place="margin">Joſ. Scalig. <hi>dicto l. p.</hi> 650.</note> 
                  <hi>Thachſaſch</hi> they kept it, which agrees alwayes with the 25. of our <hi>December,</hi> though their Intercalation falling before ours (and in their <hi>Maſcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> or our <hi>Auguſt</hi>) changes the day of the Week every Leap-year into the next after what we keep: And for that of <hi>Elkopti</hi> we ſee in a ſhort deſcription of their account, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from an Aethiopian
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Apud</hi> Scalig. <hi>diste l. p.</hi> 661.</note> Prieſt, that their <hi>Almolad,</hi> or the feaſt of the Nativity, is pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced againſt their Moneth <hi>Chiach,</hi> which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to our <hi>December,</hi> and the ſucceſſion of their Feaſts is juſt as in the <hi>Syriack</hi> account; and therefore reaſon enough is, that thence
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115666:25"/>we collect the very dayes in both to be the ſelf-ſame. And to conclude here, what greater teſtimony can there be that it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into the Church, even from the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and Apoſtles of our Saviour, than this, that it was ſo anciently obſerved, and hath been ever ſince ſo generally received through Chriſtendom? for ſo of the like things that great Father St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> pronounces,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt. ad Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuarium</hi> 118.</note> 
                  <hi>Illa quae non ſcripta,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſed tradita, cuſtodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus; quae quidem toto terrarum orbe obſervan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, dantur intelligi vel ab ipſis Apoſtolis, vel à plenariis Conciliis, quorum eſt in Eccleſiâ ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berrima authoritas, commendata atque ſtatuta retineri: Sicuti quod Domini Paſſio, &amp; Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio, &amp; Aſcenſio in coelum, &amp; adventus de coelo Spiritus Sancti, anniverſaria ſolennitate celebran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur; &amp; ſi quid aliud tale occurrerit quod ſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ab univerſâ quacunque ſe diffundit Eccleſia:</hi> All ſuch things he ſuppoſes either delivered by the Apoſtles, or ordained by general Councils; for Councils, here we have no te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony that they ordained it; therefore it reſts by this argument, that we derive it from the eldeſt tradition that may be in Chriſtianity. But we end here this inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and reſolve with that old Hymne of St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> uſed in the ſervice of this day in the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>Sic praeſens teſtatur dies,</l>
                     <l>Currens per anni circulum,</l>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:115666:26"/>
                     <l>Quod ſolus à ſede Patris</l>
                     <l>Mundi ſalus adveneris:</l>
                     <l>Hunc coelum, terra, hunc mare,</l>
                     <l>Hunc omne quod in eis eſt,</l>
                     <l>Auctorem adventûs tui</l>
                     <l>Laudans exultat cantico.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Neither find I any Chriſtian Church that in the later ages hath otherwiſe celebrated it, ſave onely that of the <hi>Armenians,</hi> who
<note n="*" place="margin">Cathalicus Armeniorum in legat. ad Arm.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained an ancient cuſtom of confounding it with the <hi>Epiphany,</hi> and that to the time of <hi>Manuel Comnenus,</hi> which is about 440. years ſince, and perhaps yet do; of which confuſion of thoſe feaſts more in the laſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph. But, becauſe in theſe proofs hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto declared, the common and moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived grounds and reaſons brought for it out of the holy Text, and ſome other, are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; as alſo on the other ſide, ſome ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections are made in later times againſt it, and that by ſuch as bear even the greateſt names in the ſtate of Learning; and ſome ancient teſtimonies alſo impugne what we have hitherto concluded: It follows next, (leſt the inquiry ſhould ſeem done with too much negligence) that we both conſider of thoſe common grounds and reaſons, and then ſhew why they were not here uſed; and furthermore, that we give ſuch anſwer to thoſe objections, and ancient teſtimonies, as that they may not at all hinder the credit of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:115666:26"/>thoſe arguments which before have ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtratively juſtified it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>SECT. V. <hi>The common Reaſons uſed out of the holy Text to juſtifie this day, and how they are miſtaken, and therefore not uſed here; together with what ſome would prove from the Scheme of his Nativity.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OF thoſe which have generally received it, the Ancients about 400. years after it have ſtriv'd to fetch reaſons for it out of the holy Writ, (being unhappily not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to rely wholly upon the tradition) and ſome of later time juſtifie it by Aſtrological obſervations; both being deceived, the firſt by miſ-underſtanding the Text, the other by too much mingling their errors in the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of Nature with the thoughts of this moſt ſacred birth-day. For thoſe Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, they knew out of
<note n="*" place="margin">Lev. 16. &amp; 23.</note> 
                  <hi>Moſes,</hi> that the High Prieſt did onely once every year enter into the Holieſt place, or the <hi>Sanctum San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum;</hi> and this is ordained to be on the 10. day of the 7. Moneth, that is, the Feaſt of <hi>Kippurim,</hi> or Expiations in <hi>Tiſri:</hi> Then out of St. <hi>Luke,</hi> they ſuppoſed that the Angel appeared to <hi>Zachary,</hi> being High Prieſt, and ſacrificing there on the ſame day which they would make agree with the 24. of <hi>September,</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:115666:27"/>(although for the very day they have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what differed in the Eaſtern Church, and ſome have alſo
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Stephanus Gobarus Trith. apud Photium, cod.</hi> 232.</note> ſuppoſed the conception in <hi>October,</hi> ſome in <hi>November</hi>) and that on the night following <hi>Zachary's</hi> Wife <hi>Elizabeth</hi> conceived St. <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> as the Apoſtle foretold him: From hence, according to the Evangeliſt, they accounted 6. Moneths; at the end of which time the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> conceived, that time falls into the 25. of <hi>March,</hi> from whence 9. Moneths being accounted, (the common time of a birth) the 25. of <hi>December</hi> found the very birth-day of our Saviour: This is the ſumme of the calculation us'd out of the holy Text by the
<note n="†" place="margin">D. Chryſoſtom. in ſape laudato Panegyrico. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtaſius Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ochenus, Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drenus chronici Alexandrini autor, &amp;c.</note> Ancients, although not without ſome confuſion of Moneths; while by reaſon of application of old Lunar Moneths to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> which are Solar, they confound herein ſometimes <hi>April</hi> with <hi>March,</hi> and <hi>September</hi> with <hi>October.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That other ſort which would prove it by Aſtrology, ſhews us the Scheme of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, erected for the altitude and Meridian of <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> to the midnight following the 25. of <hi>December,</hi> and then telling how won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully it is (by the Rules of that Art) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to ſo wonderful a birth; and anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipating ſome part of the accuſation they might juſtly look for, they declare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that they mean not that any thing tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching his Divinity, his Miracles, his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:115666:27"/>of life, or ſending forth the Goſpel, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended at all on the Stars; but they ſay, that as naturally he was of the beſt temperature, and exacteſt beauty, and had continuall health, and ſo ſingular gravity of aſpect. <hi>Sic etiam Deus optimus &amp; glorioſus</hi> (as <hi>Cardan's</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ad Ptolem. Tetrabib. l.</hi> 2. <hi>text.</hi> 54.</note> words are) <hi>optimâ conſtitutione aſtrorum atque admirabili Geneſin illius adornavit;</hi> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Heavens if the Almighty, ſayes he, had not to this purpoſe ordained to have concur'd and have been obſerved, one of theſe two things had happened; either that the very day, and hour, and minute of the hour of that birth, had not been ſo conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and diligently ever kept in the Church; or elſe that all the ſignifications in the Scheme had not been <hi>adeo ſingularia,</hi> as he writes, <hi>magnifica, glorioſa, &amp; tanto concurſu digna, tum vero omnibus quae ſucceſſerunt de vitae ſanctitate, de morum gravitate, &amp;c. adeo congruentia, ut nil exactius poſſit excogitari;</hi> and after the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars largely declared, he too boldly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes againſt ſuch as juſtly enough impugne the art of Aſtrology as groundleſs, with this, that they can now have nothing elſe left to ſpeak againſt it, as <hi>Ptolomy</hi> teaches it, than this onely, that they ſhould perhaps object, that <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> to gain credit to the profeſſion, wrote his whole <hi>Quadripartite,</hi> according to the agreement 'twixt this Scheme, which it is moſt likely he never ſaw, and the parts of our Saviours life denoted by it; than which,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:115666:28"/>ſaith he, as he well might, nothing can be more abſurd. But out of this we may eaſily ſee, that ſuch as ſtand upon thoſe learned er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors cannot but think with him, that the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day and hour of this birth is fully confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by that Scheme: Neither is there cauſe (ſo their grounds were certain) but that they might hence conclude alſo that this were the very time, although no other teſtimony were extant of it: For what want they in this pretence of that knowledge of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Tarutius,</hi> who was able (as he made ſome learned men believe) not onely to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell out of the Scheme of a Nativity, but alſo to find out of the circumſtances of any life and fortune, the very point of the birth, and ſo frame the Scheme it ſelf? as <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſayes he did both in the ſearch after <hi>Romulus</hi> his birth-day, and the firſt foundation of <hi>Rome;</hi> and the finding the exact Scheme is the ſame with finding the exact time of the birth; which thoſe Aſtrologers, it ſeems, think they have done, as well out of the congruity (as they ſuppoſe) of the Scheme to what they apply it, as out of any teſtimony or tradition of the Church.</p>
               <p>But the truth is, that both this of ſome A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologers; and that other of calculation out of the holy Text, deſerve nor place nor name of reaſon to this purpoſe: For that of the Calculation of the months out of the holy Text, the chief ground on which it inſiſts,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115666:28"/>and which being taken away it all become; meerly vain, is that of <hi>Zacharias</hi> being a High-Prieſt, and in his ſacrificing in the holieſt place, or <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum,</hi> or in the Oracle, as the names of it are varied. For a ſacrifice in that place was only in that feaſt of Expiation, that is, the 10 of <hi>Tiſri,</hi> or 7 month, and this only by the High-Prieſt; But it is moſt clear that <hi>Zacharis</hi> was no High-Prieſt, but only one of thoſe 24 courſes or ſtations of Prieſts which weekly ſerved at the Temple. For <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> diſtinguiſhed the
<note n="*" place="margin">1 Paral. 24.</note> poſterity of <hi>Eleazar</hi> and <hi>Ithamar</hi> by Lots for the continuall and daily ſervice and ſacrifice into 24 courſes, and of thoſe courſes every one had a week for attendance, ſo that after every 24 weeks the firſt came to attend again; as alſo it was in the 24 courſes of the Levites, their weeks in attendance alwaies ending on the morning of the Sabbath. Hereof is plentifull teſtimony, both in holy
<note n="†" place="margin">1 Paral. 9. <hi>comm.</hi> 25. <hi>Joſ.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 11 <hi>&amp; in vita ſua, &amp;</hi> 2 <hi>adv. Api<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem.</hi>
                  </note> writ and in the Jews Liturgies, beſides <hi>Joſeph,</hi> and the old Fathers, and it is fully and ſhortly expreſſed by <hi>Eucherius, Erant ſortes</hi> 24 (ſaith he) <hi>&amp; ſacerdotum, &amp; Levitarum &amp; Janutorum, qui per totidem ſeptimanas ſibi ex ordine ſucce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derent, ſabbato novâ turmâ intrante ad officimn, &amp; poſt ſabbatum, eâ quae proximâ ſeptimativâ miniſtraverat domum redeunte.</hi> In theſe 24 courſes the 8 is the family of <hi>Abia;</hi> of his 8 courſe was <hi>Zacharie</hi> a Prieſt, and was as
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ad l.</hi> 4. <hi>Reg. c.</hi> 23.</note>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:115666:29"/>this time in the week of his courſe building incenſe in the Temple, but not in the Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> lieft place; ſo is the Text of St. <hi>Luke; A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> certain Prieſt</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, i. <hi>of the courſed of Abia;</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Zachary;</hi> and afterward, <hi>as ſoon as the miniſtrations were accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, &amp;c.</hi> what courſe or ſpecial dayes of miniſtration to be accompliſhed could here belong to the Prieſts of the Jewes? But as <hi>Matthias,</hi> and <hi>Flavius Joſephus</hi> were
<note n="*" place="margin">1 Macab. c. 2 <hi>comm.</hi> 1 <hi>Joſ. in</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>l.</hi> 12. <hi>c.</hi> 8 <hi>&amp; in vita ſua.</hi>
                  </note> Prieſts of the Sons, or courſe of <hi>Jeho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arid.</hi> (that is, of the 1 courſe) ſo was <hi>Zacharie</hi> of <hi>Abia,</hi> or of the 8. Neither was any High-Prieſt of that age bearing any ſuch name: But he that was High-prieſt at the birth was <hi>Joazar,</hi> and his predeceſſors were <hi>Joſeph
<note n="†" place="margin">Niceph. Patriarch. in chronol. &amp;c.</note> Matthias, Simon,</hi> &amp;c. So that nothing is more certain then this, that <hi>Zacharie</hi> was not High-Prieſt; although anciently very great names were deceived, while they took him to be ſo, as St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> St. <hi>Chryſoſtome, Anaſtaſius</hi> Patriarch
<note n="*" place="margin">MS. <hi>apud</hi> Joſ. Scalig. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 509.</note> of <hi>Antioch,</hi> and others expreſly: <hi>Zachary</hi> then being no High Prieſt, it plainly follows that their whoſe calcula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Moneths here from the 10. of <hi>Tiſri.</hi> (in which onely the High Prieſt entred into the Oracle) proves nothing at all, but ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes meerly falſe grounds; and ſo no proof of the certainty of this day can be extracted out of that holy Story; and <hi>Zacharies</hi> Sacrifice, for ought appears there, might indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be on any other day of the year. We o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:115666:29"/>here their ſuppoſition of an exact num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of dayes for the natural time of a Birth, which plainly can never be known; and in ſo clear a point thus much is too much then enough.</p>
               <p>For that other reaſon or confirmation (as they would have it) out of Aſtrology, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it is moſt vain (that we may ſpeak no worſe of it) both in regard of the Art it ſelf, and alſo of this application of it. For the Art it ſelf though very many Authors are of it, yet there is none extant of any great an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity; and of thoſe which are, very few a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree to any purpoſe among themſelves. <hi>Pto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomy,</hi> who is the ancienteſt of them, whoſe Volumes of it are publickly extant, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved about CXL. years after our Saviour, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tetrabib. l.</hi> 1. <hi>comm.</hi> 57, 58, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> from what the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> before him had obſerved. The <hi>Arabians,</hi> as <hi>Haly, Albu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazar, Meſſalath,</hi> the Author of <hi>Alcabitius, Zabel,</hi> and ſuch more have another Doctrine from his. The Latins, as <hi>Manilius</hi> and <hi>Julius Firmicus,</hi> neither agree among themſelves nor with others; to omit the numerous dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences that are in the many Volums of it written in the middle and latter ages. What certainty thereof can there be in that Art whoſe Profeſſors do make no other pretence then long continuance of conſtant obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſignes, and things ſignified to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie themſelves; and yet in truth they have no teſtimony of ſuch continuance of obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation?
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:115666:30"/>And I truſt that no man will think that by rationall collection only (as in ſome other faculties) without a preceding and conſtant obſervation of many ages at leaſt, it is poſſible to diſcover the nature of this or that Star, or of the various policious of the Heavens which every minute produces. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, without ſuppoſition of a certainty, not onely of the degrees, but in ſome particulars of the minutes alſo in which this or that Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net is, the Aſtrologer proceeds not; yet it is moſt known that the Aſtronomers, from whoſe noble ſearch theſe ſuppoſitions are patiently taken by the Aſtrologers, are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in even almoſt as differing among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as the Aſtrologers in denoting of ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects; witneſſe the difference of hours in Calculation by the <hi>Alphonſine.</hi> Tables from the <hi>Prutenique,</hi> made according to <hi>Coperni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> and of both of the reſtored motions of <hi>Tycho Brahe.</hi> And two of the Planets, <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Mercury,</hi> which bear no ſmall rule in the precepts of Aſtrology, have hitherto ſcarce leſſe conceal'd their motions and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the Heavens, then <hi>Proteus</hi> would have done his true ſhape. Yet ſtill what the Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomer knows is uncertain, and ingeniouſly confeſſes to be ſo; the Aſtrologer for the moſt part ſlothfully believing, and ſo fixing himſelf on that belief, takes for his infallible ground, and ſo deceives, and is deceived in his aſpects (which he reſolves partile, when
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:115666:30"/>they may perhaps be platique, and platique when they may be partile) in his directions in the print of his <hi>Horoſcope,</hi> and the other three of his Figure in his <hi>Fines,</hi> in his <hi>Ferda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae,</hi> in his <hi>Conjunctions,</hi> and in what elſe ſtands upon ſuch exactneſſe of calculation. But this is no place to ſpeak more in particular of that Art: Enough hath been ſaid of the vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of it by <hi>Mirandula, Alexander ab Angelis,</hi> and others that have purpoſely written Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes againſt it. But for the application of it to this of our Saviours Birth-day, it is both too groundleſſe alſo in reſpect of the hour to which the Figure is erected, and withall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious in the reſt of the ſuppoſitions. For the hour, it is erected to midnight following the 29. of <hi>December,</hi> for ſo we muſt underſtand that which <hi>Cardan</hi> deſignes the time by; <hi>Die<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi> 6. (ſaith he) <hi>horis</hi> 12. <hi>ante radicem Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logorum, qui auni initium ſumunt in Calendis Januariis:</hi> This falls upon 12. of the clock of the night following the 25. of <hi>December.</hi> But whence, I wonder, was <hi>Cardan</hi> ſo ſure that this was the minute of the hour of the Birth? Some indeed that among the Ancients erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neouſly placed it on the 6. of <hi>January,</hi> took the point of midnight to be the very minute, as we ſee out of thoſe collections out of <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanus, Gobarus, Tritheites</hi> in <hi>Photius.</hi> And in ſome part of the <hi>Aſiatique</hi> Churches (eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of <hi>Syria</hi>) the night of this day hath the name of the night of the Nativity, which
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:115666:31"/>
                  <hi>Alfragan</hi> remembers. But that teſtimony of the Nativity cited out of an old Greek Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſcript in St. <hi>Marks</hi> Library at <hi>Florence</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ad Theolog. Muchamed. not.</hi> 12.</note> by <hi>Widmonſtadius,</hi> ſaies, it was <hi>hora diet ſex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta: Heſychius</hi> there alſo mentioned put in on <hi>hora diei ſeptima;</hi> with which agrees that Chronicle of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> or the <hi>Faſti
<note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>Editione Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertana p.</hi> 532.</note> Siculi</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> the 7. hour of the day. And though none of thoſe are of credit e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to juſtifie the very hour; yet, it ſeems, they all meant it a Birth of the day, and not of the night, the houres of which they alſo note by the name of the hours of the night; neither can it be cleared in the holy Text, whether it were in the night or in the day. The Angel in the night ſaies to the Shepherds, <hi>For unto you is born this day,</hi> (that is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) a Saviour, out of which words it were too much raſhneſſe to reſolve whether the point of the Birth were in the night or in the day. If then <hi>Cardan,</hi> or his followers had been led by authority, they ſhould have ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther erected the figure (if at all they erected it) to the 6. or 7. hour of the day, that is about 12. hours before their ſuppoſed time; and ſo the whole Scheme had been changed, and <hi>Aries</hi> had been the <hi>Horoſcope</hi> inſtead of <hi>Libra,</hi> and <hi>Capricorn</hi> in mid-heaven for <hi>Cancer.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides alſo, had the mid-night following the 25. day been the juſt time, thoſe which in <hi>Jewry</hi> propagated the tradition to Poſterity, ſhould (by all probability) have deliver'd it
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:115666:31"/>to have been on the 26. day of the <hi>Julian De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> not on the 25. For by the uſe of the <hi>Jews,</hi> their naturall days
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Severus A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochenus apud Anaſtaſ. Sinaſt. quaeſt.</hi> 152. <hi>praeter litt. ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cras.</hi>
                  </note> were accounted from Evening to Evening: So that the night following the 25. was part in their account of the 26. day, as alſo the Eccleſiaſticall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of days by the Cannon-Law,
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Quod die diſt.</hi> 75. <hi>&amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra de feriis c.</hi> 1 <hi>Francolin de horis canonic. c.</hi> 43. <hi>&amp; ſynod. in Trullo cani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go.</hi> 91.</note> and that from ancient time. Neither can it for this reaſon alone be ſalved, unleſſe advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of a different account of days be taken from the old uſe in the State of <hi>Rome,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto <hi>Jewry</hi> was then ſubject: For in that State the naturall day was from midnight
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>F. tit. de fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riis l.</hi> 8. <hi>&amp;</hi> Plutarch <hi>in probl. Rom.</hi> 84.</note> to midnight; yet according to that too it ſtands but indifferent to which of the two days the Birth ſhould be referred, being thus placed in the very point of midnight which parts them. Beſides alſo, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> have taken it to have been in the night<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time preceding the 25. day, for they in the Vigil of the Feaſt celebrate the Shepheards watching, and in the morning they have a ſpecial Maſſe with reference
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ordo Roman. ſed &amp; vide ſis Hugo de S. Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctore, erudit. Theol. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> to the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards viſitation of our Saviour, at that time in the Manger: So that according to their ſuppoſition, that Scheme is not for the birth, but for a day after: In ſumme, the hour is eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way uncertain, their proof therefore being thus ſhewed groundleſſe in regard of the exact hour of the natural day (which is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known) I hope there needs not much be ſaid to juſtifie that the ſuppoſitions of dependence
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:115666:32"/>twixt any working or ſignifications of the Stars, and that great and moſt ſacred myſtery of the Incarnation are moſt impious; although it were ſo that otherwiſe the traditions of that art had their place: As if either the common objects of ſenſe, or uncertain col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections of mans weak underſtanding, had ſo much to do with what but at the beſt we are able to apprehend by Faith onely. But <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan</hi> had herein example to follow in thoſe who long before him had impiouſly referr'd the beginning of Chriſtian
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Albumazar de conjunct. differ.</hi> 8. <hi>tract.</hi> 2 <hi>&amp; apud</hi> Rog. Bacon <hi>in opere majori M.S. ad Clem. P.P.</hi> 4.</note> Religion to a certain number of revolutions of <hi>Saturn.</hi> And therefore alſo he makes that Comet which in 1133. appeared in <hi>Aries</hi> under the Northern part of the Milky way, and was (as he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed) of Martial, Jovial and Mercuriall quality, to denote the Schiſms and Changes of Religion which ſoon after fell in this Kingdom under <hi>Henry</hi> 8. For to <hi>Aries</hi> (ſaies <hi>Ptolomy</hi>) is this Iſland ſubject as to a tutelar ſign. And in this Nativity alſo, that Star which St. <hi>Matthew</hi> ſpeaks of, <hi>Cardan</hi> takes for a ſignifying Comet, and places it in the Aſcendent, becauſe it ſeems he read in the Evangeliſt that the wiſe men ſaw it in the Eaſt. But there is good authority among the Ancients, &amp; that by collection out of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Text, that their ſeeing of it in the Eaſt was a continuall ſeeing of it
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>D. Auguſt. in ſerm.</hi> 1. <hi>edit.</hi> Pariſ. <hi>edit. Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanienſ. tom.</hi> 10. <hi>p.</hi> 431. <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cephor. Caliſt. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 13.</note> for two years time before the birth in the Countries, that lay Eaſt from <hi>Jewry:</hi> and doubtleſs alſo it could not be
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:115666:32"/>of any ſuch heights as Comets are at the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſuppoſed to be, neither could it have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned a particular Houſe in <hi>Bethlem,</hi> if it had been ſo high as to have been carried either as Stars or Comets are in the Diurnall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Heavens. But enough hereof is already ſaid againſt him by that great <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho Brahe,</hi> with whoſe
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Progymnaſm. de nova ſtella p.</hi> 316.</note> words alſo we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude here, that <hi>Cardan</hi> and his followers, <hi>plus impiè quam juſtâ ratione, quomodocunque tandem excuſent, hoc aſſeverant ut reliqua; pudet n. referra quae Aſtrologicis ſuis commentis hac de re inſeruit, non adducam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There was reaſon enough therefore why neither of theſe firſt kind of arguments (whereof the one is taken from a groundleſs calculation of Moneths in the holy Text, the other from the vanities of Aſtrology) were uſed among the proofs brought for the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of this Birth-day: For he that endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to eſtabliſh a truth by arguments, ſhould no leſs religiouſly abſtain from falſe premiſſes, than he ought carefully to meet with the ſharpeſt objections; leſt while the concluſion is of it ſelf true, and would clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear ſo if no other but true grounds were uſed to induce it; the credit of it be therefore ſtill queſtioned, becauſe in the foundations whereon it is ſo made to inſiſt there is ſuch uſe of apparent falſhoods: At leaſt, he rather ſeems too willing than truly able to prove, who ſo mixes truth, doubts
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:115666:33"/>and falſhood in deducing his concluſion, that either ſome of his premiſſes firſt patiently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and credited by himſelf, and then of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in his arguments, have indeed either much more need of proof, but are leſs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by him than his concluſion; or elſe are every way falſe, and ſo utterly betray both the concluſion and his judgment. But we leave theſe, and go next (as is before purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) to the Objections of late time made againſt what is hitherto concluded touching the juſt day of this ſacred birth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <head>SECT. VII. <hi>The chief Objections that are made againſt this dayes being the true time of the birth, with plain Anſwers to them.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Objections againſt this received o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion or tradition of the day made in later time are chiefly two; the one taken out of the enumeration of thoſe circular courſes, of the Prieſts divided into their 24. families, as is before expreſſed; and the other from the circumſtances of the time of the year of this birth mentioned in holy Writ. For the firſt, divers Chronologers, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they have according to their own fancies altered the years of account from our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours birth, (ſome making it one, ſome two, ſome three, ſome more years ancienter than
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:115666:33"/>the <hi>Dionyſian Epocha</hi> received in the Church) then, that they may ſettle alſo the very day of the birth, or at leaſt the time of the year wherein the day fell, they calculate by thoſe weekly miniſtrations of the 24. courſes of the Prieſts, to find out the week wherein the courſe of <hi>Abia</hi> (of which <hi>Zachary</hi> was) mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in the Temple; for then would it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that the time of <hi>Johns</hi> conception, from which the conception, and birth of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our was accounted would nearly, if not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly be found alſo. For the Text is, That <hi>after thoſe dayes</hi> (of his miniſtration) <hi>his wife</hi> Elizabeth <hi>conceived, and hid her ſelf five months, &amp;c.</hi> For example, ſome here ſuppoſing in their chronology that the birth was two years before the vulgarly-received time, and in the MMMMDCCXI. year of the <hi>Julian</hi> period, thus work in calculation to find out the time of the year when our Saviour was born; they obſerve firſt that <hi>Antiochus</hi> pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted the Temple, and diſcontinued the dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sacrifices, and ſo by conſequence the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of theſe courſes; then they ſay that <hi>Judas Macchabeus,</hi> upon the new Dedication of the Temple recontinued the daily Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and by a like conſequence reſtored the courſes, and in reſtoring of them began with the firſt, that is, the courſe of <hi>Jehoiarid,</hi> and this in the 25. day of the Hebrew Moneth <hi>Caſlea,</hi> in the MMMMDXLIX. year of the <hi>Julian</hi> period, which agrees with the 24. of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:115666:34"/>
                  <hi>November</hi> of that year; this day fell on Munday, ſo that the continuance of the courſe of <hi>Ieheiarid</hi> was (according to the firſt conſtitution) till the morning of the Sabbath following, the next Sabbath before this new Dedication of the Temples falling ſo on the 22. of <hi>November:</hi> From this renewing of the courſes they thus reckon; from the courſe of <hi>Ichoiarid,</hi> being the firſt, to that of <hi>Abia,</hi> being the eighth, muſt intercede 49. dayes; ſo that the courſe of <hi>Abia</hi> began on the 10. of <hi>Ianuary</hi> MMMMDL. year of the <hi>Iulian</hi> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod; having then before ſuppoſed that the year of the birth was the MMMMDCCXI. year of the <hi>Iulian</hi> Period, and that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of St. <hi>Iohn</hi> was in the year preceding, that is, in the year MMMMDCCX. they account over the whole cycles of thoſe 24. courſes that intercede from the courſe of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia</hi> in <hi>Ianuary</hi> of the year MMMMDL. and thence obſerve at what time the courſe of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia</hi> falls again in that MMMMDCCX. year of the <hi>Iulian</hi> Period; thus they find that in thoſe 160. years 349. of thoſe courſes being paſt, the courſe of <hi>Abia</hi> being the laſt (in this computation, which begins at the next from it) of the 349. falls exactly to begin upon the 21. of <hi>Iuly</hi> (being the Sabbath) of the year MMMMDCCX. and ſo ends upon the 28. of the ſame <hi>July,</hi> that is, the morning of the Sabbath following: By which they conclude, that upon or immediately after the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:115666:34"/>28. of the ſame <hi>July</hi> St. <hi>John</hi> was concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; according to the Text, that tells us, <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the dayes of Zacharies miniſtration, &amp;c.</hi> This being granted, it would follow that the birth of our Saviour (according to the vulgar cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation from the time of St. <hi>Johns</hi> concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) would be in <hi>October</hi> or <hi>November</hi> of the following year, that is, of the MMMMDCCXI. of the <hi>Iulian</hi> Period. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by another liberty in this kind of num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bering, placing it in <hi>September,</hi> others other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, while they fetch their arguments out of the revolutions of their courſes.</p>
               <p>The other Objection, that is, from the circumſtances of the time of the year of this birth, is out of the holy Text; where it is
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>D. Luc. c.</hi> 2. <hi>comm.</hi> 8.</note> written, that <hi>there were Shepheards in the ſame countrey abiding in the fields,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, i. <hi>and keeping watch over their flock by night,</hi> and this at the time of the birth: This, ſay ſome, of all times fits not the midſt of Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or <hi>December;</hi> but rather the Spring, Summer or Autumn, when the temper or heat of the night permit both ſheep and ſhepherd to be in the fields.</p>
               <p>But neither of theſe reaſons have any weight againſt that received tradition of the 25. of <hi>December,</hi> Firſt, for the 24. courſes, it were ſomething indeed if we exactly knew with which of the courſes <hi>Iudas Macchabe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> began his Inſtauration of the Sacrifices;
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:115666:35"/>for ſuppoſing then that from this beginning and new dedication untill <hi>Zacharies</hi> miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion no diſturbance of the continuance of thoſe courſes had hapned, &amp; alſo that had the juſt number of years fully agreed upon from the ſame dedication to our Saviours Birth, it were ſuch an argument as could not in any way be exceeded, ſo that we alſo otherwiſe allow the common calculation of time that was uſed by the Fathers out of St. <hi>Luke,</hi> in regard only of the diſtance between the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of St. <hi>Iohn,</hi> and the conception and Birth of our Saviour. For St. <hi>John</hi> was, as they commonly agree conceived preſently upon the end of <hi>Zacharies</hi> Miniſtration, and this conception once fixed were a conſtant <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocha</hi> (according to the vulgarly-receiv'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of St. <hi>Luke</hi>) from whence the time of the year at leaſt of our Saviours Birth-night may be clearly collected. But on the other ſide, if we fail in the certainty of the beginning of the courſes, who ſees not that nothing can be concluded out of them to ſatisfie ſuch a judgement as dares not rely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch conjecturall inferences without an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen clearneſſe in their antecedents? Now for that matter, no old Stories have mention of the name of that particular courſe with which <hi>Iudas Macchabaeus</hi> began; but they
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib. Haſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeorum c.</hi> 1.20 <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.52. <hi>Epit. Jaſonis c.</hi> 10.15. <hi>item Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph Ben Gori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on l.</hi> 3: <hi>c.</hi> 13.</note> onely ſhew the new dedication, in which it may be granted that there was an inſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the courſes; but whether by begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:115666:35"/>again (as they ſuppoſe) with that of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heiarid,</hi> which is firſt in <hi>Davids</hi> diſtribution, or with that of <hi>Jedaiah,</hi> being the ſecond or with any other of the 24. nothing is left to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct us; and we know that through <hi>Amio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> his prophanation of the Temple, the courſes were diſcontinued in the 143. year from <hi>Selucu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Nicanor,</hi> and that upon the 25. of <hi>Caſleu,</hi> and that upon the ſame day five years after the ſacrifices, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence the courſes were reſtored. But it is neither known what courſe was then in Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration, when <hi>Antiochus</hi> prophan'd the Temple (for we have no certain <hi>Epocha</hi> from which that can be deduced) or with what courſe the firſt week after the dedication was ſerved: How then is it poſſible to reckon by the cycles of thoſe courſes, and ſo find the juſt time of this of <hi>Abia,</hi> or the eight? No more then it might be poſſible for one who knew only we had 12 moneths in the year, but withall were wholly ignorant when the firſt began, could yet tell at what ſeaſon the 8. fell? And for that their conjecture of the beginning with the courſe of <hi>Jehoiarib,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that was the firſt in <hi>Davids</hi> diſtributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is both in it ſelf a very weak one and perhaps expreſly againſt the ſtrictneſs uſ'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Iews</hi> in obſervation of thoſe cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. For beſides that, no teſtimony at all aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures us but that any other of the courſes as well as that of <hi>Ichoiarib</hi> (according to the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:115666:36"/>of time, and fitneſſe of perſons) might be the firſt at that new dedication. We have it confeſſed by the greateſt of them which this way impugne the receiv'd tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the certainty of the cycles of thoſe 24. courſes was ſo carefully kept ſo long as the ſacrifices continued, that no one courſe might ſupply the room of another, againſt the order of ſucceſſion in their cycles: For ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, if that of <hi>Iehoiarib</hi> were for this week, then of neceſſity that of <hi>Iedaiah,</hi> being the ſecond in the cycle, muſt be for the week fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, and that of <hi>Harim</hi> for the third week, that of <hi>Seorim</hi> for the fourth, and ſo the reſt according to their ſucceſſion in the cycle; and this inſomuch, that if (for the purpoſe) that of <hi>Harim</hi> ſhould have miſſed at the Temple at the third week, after the end of the courſe of <hi>Iedaiah,</hi> yet might not the ſervice be ſupplyed either by the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing courſe of <hi>Scorim,</hi> or by the continuance of that of <hi>Iedaiah;</hi> neither might any other miniſter in the Temple that week, nor might that of <hi>Scorim</hi> (being the next in the cycle) begin till the Sabbath following. And to this purpoſe alſo,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide ſis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primis</hi> Joſ. Scalig. <hi>Iſag. canon. l.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 298.</note> they bring that old Canon of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> i. <hi>Every Prieſt and every Levite that puts himſelf into the miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any of his fellows is puniſhable with death.</hi> And by this alſo they underſtand that in <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephus,</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> where he ſaies that the daily ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:115666:36"/>failed upon the 17. day of the <hi>Macedoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> moneth <hi>Panemus</hi> (which was the 17. day of their <hi>Tammuz,</hi> whereon the <hi>Iews</hi> keep a ſolemn Faſt to this day and that this was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>i.</hi> for want of thoſe that ſhould Miniſter, as if onely (as they underſtand it) the reaſon were, becauſe the courſe of that week failed, and might not be by their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons ſupplyed either by the preceding courſe, or that which was the next week to ſucceed, nor by any other. This being thus confeſſed by them, they ſhould otherwiſe have fearched in their way of proof out of thoſe courſes accounted from the new Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation under <hi>Iudas Macchabaeus:</hi> For upon this ſuppoſition, they ſhould firſt have been ſure what had been the laſt courſe at the time of <hi>Antiochus</hi> his prophanation; then ſhould they have reckoned over the cycles from that courſe, and ſo have obſerved from which of the 24. the Miniſtration beginning on the Sabbuth, being the 23. of <hi>Caſleu</hi> in the 148. year (of <hi>Seleucus,</hi> or <hi>Dilkarnon</hi>) would hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen; and thence might they have reckoned forward to ſearch out that of <hi>Abia,</hi> in this queſtion of <hi>Zacharies</hi> Miniſtration. For if there were ſuch a carefull avoiding of ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the courſe of one by another, then followes it plainly, that it was cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly known at he time of <hi>Antiochus</hi> his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanation, to which of the courſes the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration five years from that week would
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:115666:37"/>neceſſarily belong as it was then known what courſe was in the preſent miniſtration: For example, admit five years were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete from the end of the week of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanation and diſcontinuance of the courſes under <hi>Antiochus</hi> to the end of the week of the Dedication; and ſuppoſe alſo that the firſt courſe, that is of <hi>Iehoiarid,</hi> had ſerved in the Temple in the week of prophanation, then muſt it neceſſarily firſt follow, that the courſe of <hi>Iedaiah</hi> on the ſecond, muſt have ſerved in the week following, that is, the firſt week of thoſe five years: Now in thoſe five years (taking in about a day to make the numbers round in the example) we have CCLXI. weeks, and 261. weeks are ten com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete cycles of thoſe 24. courſes, and 21. weeks of advantage to go on with to make an eleventh cycle: If then the ſtrict obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of keeping every courſe to his own week (which was as well foreſeen alwayes by the revolution of thoſe cycles as any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable Feaſt, or the Dominical letter in our Eccleſiaſtick accounts is fore-known) were in ſuch uſe, then clearly what courſe ſoever ſhould have ſerved in the ſixth week of this eleventh cycle, which in our example falls to that of <hi>Iedaiah:</hi> Reckon with him in this eleventh cycle till the 21. courſe (as the weeks require) and then the courſe of <hi>Gamul</hi> is proper to the very week of the new Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; and this way, if the courſe which
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:115666:37"/>ſerved at the prophanation were known, it were eaſie to find which of them ſhould by that tradition of the <hi>Iews</hi> have ſerved at the Dedication: But when we neither know which of them ſerved at the prophanation, nor which at the Dedication, what raſhneſs is it to rely upon a bare conjecture; and that alſo ſuch an one as is adverſe to that received tradition of the exact keeping of the cycles; and is in ſubſtance confeſſed to be ſo by ſuch as have uſed it? Theſe things thus conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it follows, that they which inſiſt upon this argument, taken from the beginning of the 24. courſes in that of <hi>Iehoiarib</hi> under <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das Macchabeus,</hi> fail in their ground, and prove nothing at all againſt our received tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: The weakneſs of their Objection al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is therein increaſed, that their chronolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy in it is ſo uncertain, that they know not clearly in what year to fix the birth; ſome of them making it one, ſome two, ſome three or more years before the common <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocha,</hi> and this alſo upon conjecture. But while they vary ſo much in the year, they have little reaſon to be confident (out of their own grounds only, wherein they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe this ſo ancient tradition) that they can in their ſuppoſed years be ſure of the very day of which no other old teſtimony in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructs them, then either what we have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore remembred, or that which ſhall preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be both delivered, and ſo cleared alſo
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:115666:38"/>that it may not have weight againſt what is already juſtified. And it might eaſily fall out, that the certain year of the birth might be forgotten, or at leaſt not ſo remembred, or the memory of it not ſo preſerved, as that later poſterity could clearly have notice of it; and yet that the day of the moneth on which the Birth ſell, might by the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of tradition (as it hath been) be clearly known. The anniverſary celebration gave the day certain to poſterity, which could not thence find any thing to rectifie them in the exactneſſe of the year, as we ſee alſo in an example of the Roman States. They clearly knew that the birth of <hi>Servius Tullius,</hi> who was the firſt that was King there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the will of the common people, firſt fell upon the <hi>Nores</hi> of ſome moneth, but they
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Macrobius, l.</hi> 1. <hi>Saturnal. c.</hi> 13.</note> knew not at all of what moneth, nor in what year, for ought appears: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they avoided publick meetings in the City upon the <hi>Nones</hi> of every moneth through the year, that ſo they might be ſure to avoid them (as ſuppoſed moſt unlucky to the State) anniverſarily upon his birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day. This anniverſary avoiding publick meetings, or Fairs, on the <hi>Nones,</hi> continued the certainty of his being born on the <hi>Nones</hi> of ſome moneth, though the moneth were unknown; and ſo did the anniverſary cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration continue from the Diſciples to the day of the moneth, though perbaps the year
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:115666:38"/>be not clearly enough certain. And there was other reaſon alſo why the certainty of the year might be unknown: For there is nothing that preſerves ſuch a certainty, but either ſuch expreſſe teſtimonie of Authors as cannot be queſtioned, or elſe a continuance of vulgar ſupputation of time from, or very near from the time of the Birth it ſelf. But we have herein had neither of theſe. For the firſt, that is, the teſtimony of old Authors, they vary in the years of <hi>Auguſtus</hi> and of the Conſuls, which are the Characters by which they deſign it; and beſides, they are not of ſuch antiquity as that we can clearly rely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them; and for that of the vulgar ſupputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of time, the common account either in Inſtruments, Letters, Receipts, or the like; was not all made by the years of our Lord, till between D. and DC. after the Birth; that is, after the time that <hi>Dionyſius</hi> made his cycle of DXXXII. by multiplication of the cycle of the Sun into the Golden number, and from that time brought
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Beda de Temp. rat. c.</hi> 45.</note> in (according to his own ſuppoſitions) the ſupputation of time by the years of our Lord. For before that age the Chriſtians uſe was, either to note times by the Conſuls of the year, as the ancient courſe of <hi>Rome</hi> was; and as we ſee in old General Councils, and in Receipts of the Emperours, in the <hi>Codes</hi> of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> and <hi>Juſtinian;</hi> whence alſo <hi>Conſtantine</hi> ordained it for a
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>C. Theodoſ. tit. de conſtit. prim. l.</hi> 1. <hi>ſi qud.</hi>
                  </note> Law; that if any Edicts or Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:115666:39"/>of the Emperours ſhould be found <hi>fine die &amp; Conſule,</hi> they ſhould be held of no au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; or elſe by that <hi>Aera</hi> (commonly called <hi>Aera Hispanica</hi>) which began under <hi>Auguſtus</hi> 38. years before the <hi>Dionyſian Epo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha</hi> of our Saviour, and was chiefly uſed in <hi>Spain;</hi> as we ſee both in the Titles of the old Councils of <hi>Sivil, Bracara</hi> and <hi>Toledo,</hi> and in the Inſcriptions of that Country; but alſo it was in uſe in <hi>Africk</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> as we may collect by moſt of the Titles of the Councils of <hi>Carthage,</hi> of <hi>Arles,</hi> and <hi>Valence;</hi> unleſs we ſuppoſe that <hi>Iſidore</hi> (from whoſe Volumes of Councils we have theſe) being a <hi>Spariard,</hi> uſed the ſupputation by that <hi>Aera</hi> in the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, without warrant of the original Copies. But we have in the very Acts of the fourth Council of <hi>Arles</hi> uſe of this <hi>Aera;</hi> which was alſo in the accounts of time at <hi>Rome,</hi> as is ſeen in the Epiſtles of Pope <hi>Leo</hi> ſubſcribed with the years of it. Others denoted the years by an account from ſome regaining of their freedom; as thoſe of <hi>Antiochia</hi> did from <hi>Epocha</hi> 48. years before our Saviour, which is the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſo frequently ſpoken of in <hi>Evagrius</hi> his Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory; or from that of <hi>Seleucus</hi> or <hi>Dhilkarnun,</hi> beginning after <hi>Alexanders</hi> death. Others from the year of the Creation as the Greek Church: others from a time that fell 283. years after our Saviour (as thoſe of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and the adjoyning Churches) that is, from
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:115666:39"/>
                  <hi>Diocleſians</hi> perſecution; which in <hi>Aegypt</hi> and <hi>Aethiopia</hi> is to this day
<note n="*" place="margin">Joſ. Scalig. <hi>de emendat. Temp. p.</hi> 465, <hi>&amp;</hi> 629.</note> retained; and by the Chriſtians that uſe <hi>Arabique</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Tarick Alſhehu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, </hi> The <hi>Epocha</hi> of the Martyrs; and among the <hi>Aethiopians</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>math Michrath,</hi> i. The year of Grace. So was alſo that of <hi>Spain</hi> in common uſe there, till ſomewhat above 300. years ſince it was by ſpecial conſtitution abrogated, and the year of our Lord made the beginning of the account of time; and this alteration is by the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Lawyers referred to <hi>Iohn</hi> the firſt King of <hi>Caſtile. Duravit (Aera) uſque ad tempora Iohannis primi</hi> (ſaith
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>ad l.</hi> 52. <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit.</hi> 3. <hi>tit.</hi> 18. de las eſcrituras.</note> 
                  <hi>Lopez</hi>) <hi>qui juſſit apponi annos Nativitatis Domini.</hi> So alſo writes <hi>Aze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedo,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>ad l.</hi> 3. <hi>Reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pil. l.</hi> 2. <hi>tit.</hi> 1. de las leges.</note> ſo others of them; whence it appears, that anciently, till long after our Saviour, no account was vulgarly made by the years of his birth in which the true year might be by a continuall tradition retain'd: and alſo, that although about the time of <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> (that is, when <hi>Dionyſius</hi> began his cycle) the courſe of reckoning from the Birth was brought into uſe, yet it was received but in few parts of Chriſtendom, &amp; that principally within <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> in the inſtruments, it ſeems, of the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi> And it is obſervable here alſo, that with us in <hi>England</hi> however our ancienteſt Stories of the time ſince Chriſtianity, both in <hi>Saxon</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:115666:40"/>and <hi>Latine,</hi> are deduced by diſtinction made out of the years of our Saviour, and that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Court of <hi>Rome;</hi> our Church-proceedings and inſtruments belonging to that juriſdiction they have anciently had, and ſtill retain an account by thoſe years; yet the characters of time, both in the plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and inſtruments of the ſecular juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, hath been ever and is chiefly by the years only of our Sovereigns, Kings or Queens; ſo are our Records diſtinguiſhed, of Pleas, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, Parlaments, and the like; ſo are the inſtruments of conveyance, and what elſe is of that nature: In which, doubtleſs, the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient courſe of computation is ſo retained, that it ſhews us that none other hath been ever proper to the practice of our ſecular ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſidiction. And although indeed at this day clearly it be not of exception or erroneous, if the times in a pleading or inſtrument be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed onely by the year of our Lord, yet anciently it was much ſtood upon under
<note n="*" place="margin">23 <hi>Ed</hi> 3. <hi>fol.</hi> 21 <hi>b.</hi> 24 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>fol.</hi> 51 <hi>a. &amp;</hi> 53 <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, when in a Writ of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity brought by the Prior of St. <hi>Trinity</hi> of <hi>London</hi> againſt an Abbot, the Prior declared upon a compoſition bearing date in ſuch a year of the Lord, and the Defendants Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel took exceptions to it, ſuppoſing that none ſhould declare at the Common Law of the year of our Lord, but of the King; but upon deliberation it was reſolved good, for this reaſon onely, becauſe the compoſition
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:115666:40"/>had onely the date of the Lord; as if proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and neceſſarily otherwiſe it ſhould have been of the year of the King: And ſo, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, did they think who in the times of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, and King <hi>Iohn,</hi> not onely carefully uſed the years of the King onely, as at this day; but alſo in Recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſances entred
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Archia. de temp. reg. Joh. &amp; Hen.</hi> 3.</note> for payment of money a year or two after the entry, they denoted the time of payment by the year of the King, that ſhould happen onely if he reigned ſo long; as in the 41. of <hi>Henry</hi> the Third the Recogniſance ſhould bind the Recogniſor to pay money in 42. or 43. of his Reign. All which further conſirms, that the computati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of time by the years of our Lord, even after ſuch time as it came at all to be in uſe, hath not been near ſo vulgarly received as the anniverſary celebration of the day of the birth, under the name of the old civil Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice or the 25. of <hi>December;</hi> and therefore it may eaſily be, that the very year may be uncertain for want of ſuch a continuance of tradition, which might have come to us from the time of the birth, if from thence a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation received at firſt in the Church had continued it. But the yearly celebration or memory continued even from the eldeſt of Chriſtian time, hath taught us the exact day of the Moneth; therefore we have reaſon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough ſtill to reſolve on it.</p>
               <p>But alſo for farther ſearch into what may
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:115666:41"/>at all afford us any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ertainty of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe that Miniſtred at the time of St. <hi>Jol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception; if we firſt believe the perpetual continuance of them according to the ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in their cycles, and then alſo the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of an old <hi>Jew</hi> touching the courſe that ſerv'd at the ſecond deſtruction of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple under <hi>Vespaſian,</hi> ſhall ſo have another time then hath been yet mentioned for the courſe of <hi>Abia</hi> in the conception of St. <hi>John,</hi> and by conſequence another Birth-day of our Saviour, if we keep ſtill the vulgar ſupputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of time collected out of St. <hi>Luke.</hi> That Jew is <hi>Rabbi Joſe,</hi> whoſe words in the <hi>Seder Olam
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Edit. Baſil. p.</hi> 125.</note> Rabba</hi> are theſe; when the Temple was firſt deſtroyed, it was Evening of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, and the end alſo of the Sabbatical year, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, <hi>and the weekly courſe was that of Jehoiarib, and it was day of Ab;</hi> and ſo it was alſo in the time of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond deſtruction. If we find the courſe of <hi>Jehoiarib</hi> fixed at the ſecond deſtruction un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Veſpaſian,</hi> that is, in the 70. year of the vulgar account from the birth, and that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the beginning of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> to which the 9. day of <hi>Ab</hi> anſwers: From hence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reckon by the cycles backwards into the year that precedes the <hi>Julian</hi> year, in which our Saviours birth is commonly fixed, and ſo between the beginning of this <hi>Auguſt</hi> in the year of the deſtruction, and the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:115666:41"/>of <hi>Auguſt</hi> preceding the vulgarly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed time of the conception of St. <hi>John,</hi> will intercede <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1. complete years, that is, 154. cycles of thoſe courſes of 24. and 9. courſes over; therefore plainly in that year the courſe of <hi>Ichoiarth</hi> is about the 9. week from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> that is, in the end of <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember;</hi> and ſo it follows, that the end of the courſe of <hi>Abia,</hi> being the 8. fell in the end of <hi>November,</hi> or 8. weeks later than in the old calculation, which placed it in the end of <hi>September:</hi> And the birth of St. <hi>Iohn</hi> (as it is now celebrated) would thus have been in the 7. Moneth from the conception, which in nature were reaſonable enough; but the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>D. L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>c: c.</hi> 1. <hi>com.</hi> 36. <hi>&amp;</hi> 56.</note> Text well endures the common and moſt ancient interpretation, which denotes it to be in the 9. at leaſt. And were this autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of <hi>Rabbi Ioſe</hi> to be inſiſted on, and the perpetual ſucceſſion in the cycles of thoſe courſes in this age preceding the deſtruction to be reſolved on, there were cauſe enough here to ſeek for another expoſition of the time of the birth out of the words of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Text<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For the common account from <hi>Zacharies</hi> Miniſtration will ſo fall wholly, unleſs we change the vulgarly-received year of our Saviours birth, and (as ſome do) place three or four years back more than the <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſian</hi> account doth; for ſo will the courſe of <hi>Abia</hi> be brought into <hi>September:</hi> and if we make it fall four years ſooner (as <hi>Suſligd</hi>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:115666:42"/>doth) that courſe with and alſo in the end of <hi>Septemb.</hi> according to the common calculation herein uſed by the Fathers: But I will avoid here the making of ſuch uncertainties of thronology of years to be arguments to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte what is otherwiſe certain enough in the day. Neither can we rely here, either upon the perpetual ſucceſſion of the courſe, or on the teſtimony of that Rabbi; for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant continuance of the courſes in their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, there is great reaſon in this time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Auguſtus</hi> to doubt of it, in regard both of the Jews doing frequently otherwiſe than their Canons bind them, as alſo in regard of ſome meer neceſſity which might occaſion ſome change in the ſucceſſion, when they were in thoſe later dayes ſubject to the State of <hi>Rome.</hi> And for that of the courſe of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoiarib</hi> then miniſtring, there is not credit enough in the Author to make us believe him: For, beſides that while he tels us ſo, he is miſtaken in the true day of the ſecond deſtruction of the Temple, which fell on the 10. of <hi>Lous</hi> or <hi>Auguſt,</hi> in that
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Joſeph</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> year, not on the 4. which anſwers to his 9. of <hi>Ab;</hi> the Sacrifices, and ſo the courſes of the Prieſts ceaſed about three weeks before, that is, on the 17 day of the Moneth <hi>Tamuz,</hi> and this for the want of Prieſts, as <hi>Ioſephus,</hi> who knew it of himſelf, expreſly hath written: But he tels us not a word of what courſe then miniſtred, no more doth <hi>Abraham Ben Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:115666:42"/>in his <hi>Cabala,</hi> or he that extracted the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Olam Zuta</hi> out of the <hi>Seder Olam Rabba,</hi> where this is reported from <hi>Rabbi Ioſe;</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though both theſe Authors ſpeak moſt parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly of the ſecond deſtruction of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but they abſtain from this of the courſe then in ſervice, as from what had been deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered without warrant by <hi>Rabbi Ioſe,</hi> who indeed had learned from an old groundleſs tradition, that at the firſt deſtruction under <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> the courſe of <hi>Iohoiarib</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the Temple, and that this ſecond de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction was upon the ſame day of the ſame Moneth which the firſt was on; and becauſe he would have all in both deſtructions alike, he added alſo, that the courſe of <hi>Iehoiarib</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved now at the ſecond deſtruction, when in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed no ſervice at all was in the Temple, and that the Sacrifices and Miniſtration were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: So before the deſtruction other teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony is in the <hi>Iews</hi> Liturgy, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms that of <hi>Ioſephus</hi> to be infallible; on the Faſt of their ſeventeenth of <hi>Tamuz</hi> they ſing <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> i. <hi>Becauſe in this day the continual Sacrifice cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, this day the continual Sacrifice was taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way:</hi> If the Sacrifices then, and the courſes with them (for the one of them is not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the other) ceaſed on the 17. day of <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muz,</hi> what credit is to be given to him that tels us what courſe miniſtred in the Sacrifices three weeks after? which being ſo cleared,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:115666:43"/>there is nothing remaining in the cycles of thoſe courſes that can impugne the received tradition of this birth-day.</p>
               <p>And for that other argument of the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds watching in the night, what makes that againſt this of <hi>December?</hi> as if the ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds might not properly be in the fields watching their ſheep in the night at the midſt of Winter, eſpecially in ſo warm and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually temperate a Climate: For, although in <hi>Italy</hi> the precepts of Husbandry were, that in the Winter their ſheep ſhould be kept in Coats
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Virgil. Georg.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp; vide Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumel. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>Varre. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp; Pallad. in Novemb.</hi>
                  </note> rather than in Fields, yet they had their Winter-feedings abroad alſo; and the Climate of <hi>Bethlehem</hi> is of leſs latitude by ten degrees than that of <hi>Rome,</hi> and is alſo by ſo much the more temperate alwayes; and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in our Climate, which is much colder than either of them, we have watching of ſheep, feeding, or remaining in the fields, at this time of the year. The reſt objected out of the circumſtances of time, as that the birth of the Redeemer of all men ſhould be on that day on which the creation of the firſt man was, that is, as they without ground ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, on the 25. of <hi>March,</hi> and ſuch like, are far more vain, and not worthy of menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Theſe things being at length cleared, we need not, I truſt, be at all moved by the oppoſition of thoſe learned men, <hi>Beroald, Paulus de Midleburgo, Suſlyga, Ioſeph Scali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Kepler,</hi> (although he ſtands fot the ſame
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:115666:43"/>time of the year, but relies on the tradition of the day) <hi>Wolfius, Hoſpinian, Lidiat, Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſius, Caſaubon,</hi> and the reſt that have both made it a queſtion, and ſhewed alſo their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions againſt it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <head>SECT. VIII. <hi>Some other opinions among the ancients touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, and how ſome of them may agree with what we have received, and the reſt are of no weight againſt it; and there more especially of the ancient confuſion of this Feaſt with that of the</hi> Epiphany.</head>
               <p>BUt we have hitherto omitted the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent opinions among the ancients, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the day of this Birth; which ſhall be therefore next collected, and then alſo it ſhall be ſhewed, that they bear no weight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt what is before concluded. Thoſe opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions (as they are delivered) are various, and chiefly five. The firſt is of them who taught it to be on the 25. day of the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Moneth <hi>Pachon,</hi> which is the 20. of <hi>May</hi> in the firſt <hi>Aegyptian</hi> year. For after that the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Moneth <hi>Thoth</hi> was fixed in the end of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> and ſo the reſt of the following Moneths (30. days being allowed to a Moneth, which with the five <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> make up the whole common year) both the Fathers, and the moſt of prophane writers
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:115666:44"/>commonly uſed the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Moneths as fixed; and not as they are wandring in the years of <hi>Nabonaſſar</hi> in the <hi>Almageſt,</hi> this of the 25. of <hi>Pachon</hi> is delivered in <hi>Clemens A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandrinus,</hi> that lived ſome eighty years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Stremat.</hi> 1.</note> Apoſtles. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (ſaith he) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. There are ſome alſo that more curiouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>note, not only the year, but the very day alſo of the Birth of our Saviour; which they ſay was on the 25. of <hi>Pachon</hi> in the 28. year of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> where the account is not by the common years of <hi>Auguſtus</hi> deduced from the death of <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi> but by the years that were paſt from the
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide ſis Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorin. de die Natali c.</hi> 21.</note> taking of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi> and the death of <hi>Anthony.</hi> The ſecond (that ſeems to differ here) is in the Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle (of
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Edit. Rader. p.</hi> 533.</note> 
                  <hi>Alexandria,</hi> where it is delivered that the birth was on the 25 day of the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian</hi> Moneth <hi>Choiac,</hi> which is the 21. of the <hi>Iulian December.</hi> The third is of thoſe which ſuppoſed the day to have been
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Clem. Alex. Stremat.</hi> 1.</note> on the 24. or 25. of <hi>Pharmathi,</hi> (that is, the Moneth preceding <hi>Pachon</hi>) which agrees with the 19. or 20. of <hi>April:</hi> And with this may be reckoned the 4. which is found in <hi>Mahomet,</hi> that ſaies it was upon the 23. of the <hi>Arabique</hi> Moneth <hi>Rumadhau,</hi> but in what year he deſignes not. But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever in the <hi>Hagaren</hi> or <hi>Arabian</hi> year, this
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:115666:44"/>cannot come near our <hi>December,</hi> for accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that year of the Moneth <hi>Ramadhau</hi> falls in <hi>Iune</hi> and <hi>Iuly,</hi> about the time of our Saviours birth, <hi>Vigeſimo tertio die Ramadhan</hi> (are the words in the Tranſlation of a moſt impious Book of his long ſince done by <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannus</hi>) <hi>natus eſt Chriſtus filius Mariae, ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones Dei ſuper eum,</hi> For the <hi>Mahumedans</hi> celebrate our Saviour as a great Prophet, and his Birth, of the <hi>Virgin Mary</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Alcor. Azoar.</hi> 5. <hi>Cantacuzon</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4. <hi>&amp; Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtel. de Orbis concord. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 3 <hi>&amp; l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>ad cap. Eltur.</hi>
                  </note> alſo is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated in their <hi>Alcoran;</hi> although with much difference from the holy Story, as moſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things are which occurre there with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to either of the Teſtaments. A fifth is of thoſe who thought the day to be the 11 of the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Moneth <hi>Tybi,</hi> that is, the 6. of our <hi>Ianuary,</hi> on which we celebrate the <hi>Epiphany:</hi> So <hi>Epiphanius,</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>tom.</hi> 1. <hi>haereſ.</hi> 51. <hi>ita etiam ad extr. l.</hi> 3.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The Birth-day (of our Saviour) that is, the <hi>Epiphaby</hi> fell upon the 6. day of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> being the 11. of the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Moneth <hi>Tybi;</hi> which opinion is remembred by <hi>Stephanus Gobarus
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Apud Phot. cod.</hi> 232.</note> Tritheithes,</hi> where yet the fifth of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary</hi> is in the ſtead of the 6. as alſo in ſome places of ſome Editions of <hi>Epiphanius:</hi> But <hi>Stephanus</hi> plainly meant the 6. day, for he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprets it by the 8. <hi>Ides</hi> of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> which is the 6. day; and herewith agrees the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon opinion of the ancient Church of <hi>Egypt,</hi> which kept the Feaſt of the Birth on the 6.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:115666:45"/>of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> ſo confounding it with the Feaſt of his Baptiſm: <hi>Callian</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Collat.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>&amp; vid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſis O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rig. homil. de diverſ.</hi> 8.</note> relates ſo of him; <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trae Egypti regionem mos iſte antiquâ traditione ſervatur, ut peracto Epiphaniorum die, quem provinciae illius ſacerdotes, vel Dominici Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmi, vel ſecundum carnem Nativitatis eſſe defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niunt; &amp; idcircò utriuſque Sacramenti ſolenni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem, non bifariam, ut in occiduis provinciis, ſed ſub unâ diei hujus feſtivitate concelebrant,</hi> &amp;c. And other
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>D. Hier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. ad Ezethiel l.</hi> 1: <hi>D. Chryſ. tom.</hi> 2: <hi>edit. Eraſmianâ p.</hi> 119:</note> teſtimonies there are of this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Feaſt on the 6. day with the <hi>Epiphany.</hi> But there is none of theſe opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions but that may be either ſo interpreted, that they may ſtand with what is before delivered of the 25. of <hi>December,</hi> or elſe ſo ſhewed to inſiſt upon falſe, or no grounds, that they are no authority at all againſt it. For the firſt, which caſts it on the 25. of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chan,</hi> and is very ancient; it may be well interpreted to agree with this of <hi>December,</hi> for in conſideration of it we muſt, firſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that according to the old <hi>Iews,</hi> there was among the Fathers of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive times a reckoning of their Moneths as well by the order of enumeration as by proper names; ſo that <hi>September</hi> and <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> were known as well by the names of the 7. and 8. Moneths (as alſo their names de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>note) as by their names themſelves being accounted from <hi>March,</hi> which was the firſt. But the Greek Fathers frequently took <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pril,</hi> inſtead of <hi>March,</hi> for the firſt Moneth of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:115666:45"/>the year, as we ſee expreſly in St.
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>In Panegyr.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom,</hi> in <hi>Anaſtaſius
<note n="*" place="margin">MS. <hi>apud Scal. deemend. p.</hi> 509.</note> Patriarch</hi> of <hi>Antioch,</hi> in thoſe Conſtitutions
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 4 <hi>Cedren. p.</hi> 143 <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> attributed to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles in
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Homilia</hi> 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Macarius
<note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>Apud Photi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um cod.</hi> 232.</note> Stephanus, Gobarus,</hi> and in other teſtimonies of the ancients, where the <hi>Iulian April</hi> is made the firſt, as the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Moneth <hi>Niſan</hi> was; and therefore alſo they had the very day of this Birth known by the name of the 25. day of the 9. Moneth <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> being the 9. from <hi>April;</hi> and this kind of noting it is like enough to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived thoſe which ſaid it was on the 25. of <hi>Pachon;</hi> for <hi>Pachon</hi> is the 9. Moneth rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned from <hi>Thoth,</hi> being the firſt among the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> as <hi>December</hi> is, being accounted from <hi>April;</hi> ſo that when the tradition was delivered in thoſe terms of the 9. Moneth, no deſighation being of the account of the Moneths, nor of what Moneths were meant, it was perhaps raſhly received by ſome, and inſtead of the 25. of the 9. Moneth in the Roman year (account to that account of the Fathers) it was apprehended to be, and ſo by miltaking placed on the 25. of the 9. of the <hi>Egyptian</hi> year; neither is this conjecture for intetpretation of the originall of that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaking ſo new, but the others, and thoſe which are very learned and
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Herword &amp; Replerus. Vide Repler. de anno natali c.</hi> 15.</note> judicious, have alſo uſed it; and by a like or eaſier way may the ſecond which is before related be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood: For though the 25. of <hi>Choiac</hi> fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the 21. of <hi>December,</hi> taken ſtrictly accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:115666:46"/>to the <hi>Egyptian</hi> account from the firſt of <hi>Thoth,</hi> being the 29. of <hi>Auguſt;</hi> yet in regard that all <hi>December,</hi> except the laſt five days, falls within <hi>Choiac,</hi> and ſo the very Birth-day in the ſame Moneth, that is, on the 29. of <hi>Choiac</hi> (which truly anſwers to the 25. of <hi>December</hi>) it is reaſon enough that we ſuppoſe that <hi>Choiac</hi> was taken there for <hi>December</hi> it ſelf, ſo that the 25 of the one and the other-went with the Author for the ſame day: And ſuch examples are fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, as applying of <hi>Hebrew, Arabique, Greek</hi> and <hi>Egyptian</hi> Moneths to the <hi>Roman;</hi> and therefore alſo the Tranſlator of that Chronicle hath well expreſſed it (pref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing upon this reaſon) by the 25. of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember;</hi> For the third and fourth neither of them having any ground at all, are as eaſily and as reaſonably denyed as affirmed, nothing is brought to juſtifie them, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as little will ſerve to confute them; eſpecially that of <hi>Mahome<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> can have little weight here, when as he is ſo falſe in the whole relation of the Birth of our Saviour, in his <hi>Alcoran,</hi> that he makes the Virgin <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> to be the ſame with <hi>Marre,</hi> or <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>riam</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Az<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>r.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 29.</note> the Siſter of <hi>Aharon;</hi> and talks of <hi>Zach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> being three days onely dumb; and of our Saviours precepts given as ſoon as he was born, touching Prayers and Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es (as <hi>Robert Reading,</hi> that anciently tranſlated the <hi>Alcoran,</hi> turnes it; but the word be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:115666:46"/>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Zachawath,</hi> frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly occurring in the <hi>Alcoran</hi> for Alms or good works, is in that place by <hi>Poſtellus</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">a <hi>De O bis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiâ l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> tranſlated Tithes; it being indeed in the <hi>Arabique</hi> Teſtament
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Fpiſt; ad E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bud. c.</hi> 7. <hi>comm.</hi> 4.</note> expreſly uſed for firſt fruits alſo) with other impudent falſhoods like the reſt which are every where in that abſurd Volume of his Law; and there alſo the ſeaſon of the year is noted by a tale of the Bleſſed Virgins having dates pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently upon the Birth (which as the <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulmans</hi> ſay)
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Poſtellus de Orbis concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diâ l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> is yet growing. But for the fifth opinion, which is from confounding of the Feaſts of the <hi>Epiphany</hi> with this of the Birth, (a cuſtom alſo retained in the latter ages
<note n="†" place="margin">Catholicus Armen an legat. ad Armenios.</note> in the Churches of <hi>Armenia</hi>) and made by <hi>Stephanus, Gobarus, Treitheites</hi> in his Contrarieties of ancient opinions of the Church, to be the main and as the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one that croſſes that of the 25. of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember;</hi> however it be ſo often taken clear in <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> and raſhly alſo affirmed by the Generall or Patriarch of the <hi>Armeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> that all Churches had obſerved it ſo even from the Apoſtles: yet doubtleſſe there is great reaſon that we ſhould think that this confuſion began both without any ſufficient ground, and was alſo bred by ſome ſuch miſtakings as may be obſerved to have been in their conſideration, both of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:115666:47"/>the name and time of the Feaſt of the <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phany.</hi> For their grounds (beſides what is in miſtaking the name and circumſtances of the time of this Feaſt) there appears none that hath any colour of power of truth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe which have ſo noted it: But for the name firſt of the <hi>Epiphany,</hi> the Feaſt being anciently obſerved for the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide ſis A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>m. Marcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. l.</hi> 21. <hi>in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ſtantio &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>tano. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> homil. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 8.</note> Baptiſm of our Saviour in <hi>January</hi> as at this day; and that in the Eaſtern Churches, before ſuch time as they had learned of the Weſtern the true day of the Birth, they firſt thought that the tradition of the Feaſt under the name of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, might well denote the Birth it ſelf, and ſo teach them that on this very day our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour was born; for the Birth being of it ſelf the firſt apparition of the Son of God in the Fleſh, and <hi>Epiphania</hi> denoting in the language of the then both paſt and preſent ages the apparition of a Deity (as is eſpecially noted alſo by the moſt learned <hi>Caſaubon</hi>) they took it at length here to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>note alſo the firſt apparition of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out to the World, and that in the Feaſt-day kept on the 6. of <hi>January;</hi> and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concluded that this was the Birth-day. Now for the circumſtance of the time of the <hi>Epiphany,</hi> this confuſion of the Feaſts doubtleſſe was much confirmed to them by an interpretation of a paſſage of Saint <hi>Luke,</hi> where the Baptiſm of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:115666:47"/>(which is celebrated in the <hi>Epiphany,</hi> though <hi>Epiphanius</hi> place that alſo upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther day in <hi>November</hi>) is delivered to have been, when he was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>i.</hi> beginning to be about 30. years of age; which words are interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by ſome as if he had been of 30. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete, and beginning to be 31. on that day, which muſt ſo of neceſſity be on his birth-day: And ſo this way alſo one and the ſame day became ſacred among them to the Baptiſm and the Birth. But all this and what other miſtakings the Greek Church herein had was embraced by the moſt of them, but till they were better informed from the Weſtern Church: and the Generall of the <hi>Armenians</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">In leg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> ad Armen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>n.</note> expreſly tells <hi>Theorianus</hi> (who objects to him that Sermon of Saint <hi>Chyſoſtom</hi> touching it) that they knew not yet, nor had not heard of any Sermon of St. <hi>Chryſoſtoms</hi> to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: So that want of inſtruction onely continued this errour among them, which hath been long ſince reformed in the <hi>Syri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, Egyptian,</hi> and <hi>Ethiopian</hi> Churches, as well as in the Greek; as is before ſhewed in their agreement with us in the celebration of this Birth: But for thoſe collections out of the name of the <hi>Epiphany,</hi> and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of time of the Baptiſm, it will ſoon appear that they juſtifie nothing here againſt the received tradition. And firſt
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:115666:48"/>for that of the name of <hi>Epiphania,</hi> deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the apparition of a Deity, it is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe enough ſatisfied; and there was no need at all to have it reſtrained to the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Birth-day: For though the work <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> be uſed in the holy
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 2. <hi>ad Timoth. c.</hi> 1. <hi>comm.</hi> 10.</note> Text, both for the firſt appearing of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, or his Incarnation, as alſo for his coming at the
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Panegyr.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>tom.</hi> 5. <hi>edit. Savil. p.</hi> 525.</note> laſt day; yet in the firſt inſtitution of this Feaſt of the <hi>Epiphany,</hi> it was uſed (I ſuppoſe) for neither, but for that publick apparition or Manifeſtation (by which the Latin Fathers denote <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phania</hi>) of him to the World at his Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, in regard whereof he was before but privately known. So expreſly Saint <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> whoſe authority is here beyond exception; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſaith he, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Why then is it called <hi>Epiphanie?</hi> (in regard, as he before had ſaid, it is not the celebration of the Birth-day, but of the day of the Baptiſm;) becauſe (ſaith he) when he was born, he was not then ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted to all men, but when he was bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized; for till then he was unknown to the multitude: and to this purpoſe alſo he brings that of Saint <hi>John, I baptize with water, but there ſtandeth one among you whom ye know not,</hi> ſpeaking of our Saviour and the ſame E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſt
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:115666:48"/>expreſly; <hi>I knew him not,</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>i. That he might be manifeſted to</hi> Iſrael; <hi>therefore I came bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing with water.</hi> So Saint <hi>Jerom</hi> tells
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>In commen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. ad Ezechiel. l.</hi> 1.</note> us what the name of <hi>Epiphany</hi> denotes; <hi>Signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficat</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>baptiſma in quo aperti ſunt Chriſto Coeli, &amp; Epiphaniorum dies hucuſque venerabilis eſt, non, ut quidem putant, nata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis in carne, tunc enim abſconditus eſt &amp; non apparuit.</hi> Others of the Fathers have as much.</p>
               <p>Hereto may be added the conſent of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, after ſuch time as the true day of the birth was diſcovered to them in the Eaſtern Church; and in a Poem (as they call it) u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Service of the <hi>Epiphany</hi> in the Greek Church, made by
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Euchologium p.</hi> 93 <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Sophronius</hi> Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> an expreſs paſſage is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to this purpoſe; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. i. <hi>We glorifie thee that art with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Father of a Mother, and without Mother of a Father; and in a preceding Feaſt</hi> (of the Nativity) <hi>we knew thee an Infant, but in this preſent Feaſt</hi> (of the Epiphany) <hi>we ſee thee at full growth, appearing to be our moſt perfect God.</hi> According whereto alſo St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Serm. in E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> diverſis</hi> 64.</note> hath expreſs words, and that often: For howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they had anciently in the Greek Church confounded the Feaſts of the Baptiſm, or
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:115666:49"/>
                  <hi>Epiphany,</hi> and the Nativity; yet, being admoniſhed from the Weſtern Church, they confeſſed their error in this, that they ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd the commemoration of the Baptiſm from this of the Birth, and placed the Birth on his proper day in <hi>December;</hi> and yet they retained ſtill for the Baptiſm the name of <hi>Epiphania,</hi> which alſo is ſometimes
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide ſis The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onhil. Alexand. in edicto tom. bibl. Patrum edit. Pariſ. p.</hi> 161.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as in the <hi>Menology,</hi> and in the <hi>Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loevangela</hi> of the Greek Church, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, i.e. <hi>On the ſixth of the ſame moneth the holy Theopha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> for then was the firſt publick apparition of his Godhead. In the Church of <hi>Egypt</hi> alſo this day is ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally kept by the
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Comput. El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cophi apud Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig. de emendat. l.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 661.</note> name of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Alchamim,</hi> i. the Feaſt of Waſhing or Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; <hi>Quod Eccleſia vetus</hi> Aegyptiaca <hi>bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmum eo dic iteraret,</hi> ſayes <hi>Ioſeph Scaliger;</hi> though perhaps that name may have refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to that old cuſtom uſed in the Church, of providing water in the night of that day for the holy uſes of the whole year follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; which St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>edit. Savil. p.</hi> 524. <hi>tom</hi> 5.</note> remembers, and is yet retained in the Greek Church (as it appears by their <hi>Euchologium</hi> or Common-Prayer-Book) as alſo in the <hi>Syriack</hi> Church, which hath this Feaſt ſevered (as ours here) from the Birth, and keeps it
<note n="†" place="margin">iridimonſtad. in ſubaexis Taſt. Syriaco.</note> under the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:115666:49"/>name of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Ilhada di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nohora,</hi> i. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, (as <hi>Nazianzen</hi> calls it) or the Feaſt of Lights; and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Didinacha,</hi> i. e. Of Light ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in the Eaſt; according where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to alſo they, as others, uſe in this Feaſt great ſtore of Lights; which hath reference to the very word <hi>Epiphania</hi> doubtleſs, which denotes Enlightning alſo, or Illumination in the Vulgar Tranſlation of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament; and both in that ſenſe, as alſo in the other of Apparition or Manifeſtation, it may verbally beſides ſignifie the apparition of the Star to the Wiſe men:
<q>
                     <l>Stella, quae Solis rotam</l>
                     <l>Vincit decore ac lumine.</l>
                  </q> As <hi>Prudentius</hi> of it: and <hi>Sedulius</hi> of the Wiſe men,
<q>
                     <l>Stellam ſequentes praeviam,</l>
                     <l>Lumen requirunt lumine.</l>
                  </q> Both in their Hymnes made proper to this of the <hi>Epiphany.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that the name of the <hi>Epiphany</hi> is from the ancient and primitive times fully ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, either in that of the Baptiſm, or in the apparition of the Star: Whence alſo the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:115666:50"/>
                  <hi>Dutch, French, Italian</hi> and <hi>Spaniard</hi> note it by The day of the three Kings, for ſo thoſe wiſe men are commonly reputed to have been; and alſo the Feaſt it ſelf hath been long ſince, after the truth learned from the Weſtern Church, obſerved apart by it ſelf, as having in the firſt obſervation of it no community with this of the Birth-day; and that among thoſe which before had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded them. It follows then, that even by their own confeſſion that had been the Authors of this confuſion, they had been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in application of the name of <hi>Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> to the birth of our Saviour: and for that collection of time out of the teſtimony of St. <hi>Luke,</hi> it is clear that no certainty of the day can be thence extracted; the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, i. as it were about, expreſly excludes ſuch certainty: So St. <hi>Iohn,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, i. <hi>it was about the tenth hour,</hi> which clearly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notes not the beginning or end of the hour; neither needs there farther proof of the weakneſs of that collection.</p>
               <p>At length to conclude therefore, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities of the Ancients, and the conſent of Chriſtian Churches for this Birth-day, as it is now anniverſarily kept, being as before declared, the miſtaken reaſons being reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted (leſt their falſhoods might prejudice the clearneſs of the Truth) the Objections of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter time being anſwered, and the different Opinions of the Ancients touching it being
<pb facs="tcp:115666:50"/>either groundleſs, or not in truth oppoſing it; it reſts that we reſolve on it, as upon as certain and clear a Truth of Tradition, as by rational inference, by expreſs teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Ancients, by common and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual practice of ſeverall Churches, and by accurate inquiry, may be diſcovered.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:115666:51"/>
            <head>Theſe Books following are printed for <hi>Natha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nael Brook,</hi> and we to beſold all his Shop at the Angel in <hi>Cornhill.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Excellent Tracts in Divinity, Controverſies, Sermons, Devotions.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THe Catholick Hiſtory collected and gathered out of Scripture, Councils and ancient Fathers, in anſwer to Dr. <hi>Vain</hi>'s Loſt ſheep returned home: by <hi>Edward Cheſenſale</hi> Eſq; in <hi>octavo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Biſhop <hi>Morton</hi> on the Sacrament, in <hi>fol.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The grand Sacriledge of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in taking away the ſacred Cup from the Laity at the Lords Table: by Dr. <hi>Dan. Featly,</hi> in <hi>quarto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Quakers cauſe at ſecond hearing, being a full anſwer to their Tenets.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Re-aſſertion of Grace, <hi>Vindiciae Evangelii,</hi> or the Vindication of the Goſpel, a Reply to Mr. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony Burges's Vindiciae Legis,</hi> and to Mr. <hi>Rutherford:</hi> by <hi>Robert Towres.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Anabaptiſt anatomiz'd and ſilenced, or a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute with Mr. <hi>Tombs:</hi> by Mr. <hi>J. Cragg,</hi> where all may receive clear ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>A Cabinet Jewel; Mans miſery, Gods mercy, in 8. Sermons, with an Appendix concerning Tithes, with the expediency of marriages in publick aſſemblies: by the ſame Author Mr. <hi>Iohn Cragg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. A Glimpſe of Divine Light, being an explication of ſome paſſages exhibited to the Commiſſioners at
<pb facs="tcp:115666:51"/>
                  <hi>White-hall</hi> for approbation of publick Preachers, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>I. Harriſon</hi> of <hi>Land Chappel, Laneaſhire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. The Zealous Magiſtrate, a Sermon by <hi>T. Threſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos, quarto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. New Jeruſalem, in a Sermon for the Society of Aſtrologers, <hi>quarto,</hi> in the year 1651.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Divinity no enemy to Aſtrology, a Sermon for the Society of Aſtrologers in the year 1643. by Dr. <hi>Thomas Swadling.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>Britannia Rediviva,</hi> a Sermon before the Judges, <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1648. by <hi>I. Shaw</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Hull.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. The Princeſs Royal, in a Sermon before the Judges, <hi>March</hi> 24. by <hi>I. Shaw.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. Judgment ſet and Books opened, Religion tryed whether it be of God or man, in ſeveral Sermons, by <hi>I. Webſter, quarto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. Iſraels Redemption, or the prophetical Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of our Saviours Kingdom on Earth: by <hi>K. Matton.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15. The cauſe and cure of Ignorance, Error and Prophaneneſs; or a more hopeful way to grace and ſalvation: by <hi>K. Young, octavo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. A Bridle for the Times, tending to ſtill the murmuring, to ſettle the wavering, to ſtay the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring, and to ſtrengthen the fainting: by <hi>I. Brinſley</hi> of <hi>Yarmouth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="17">17. Comforts againſt the fear of death; wherein are diſcovered ſeveral evidences of the work of grace: by <hi>I. Collins</hi> of <hi>Norwich.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="18">18. <hi>Jacobs</hi> ſeed, or the excellency of ſeeking God by prayer: by <hi>Jer. Burroughs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="19">19. The ſumme of Practical Divinity, or the grounds of Religion in a Catechiſtical way: by Mr. <hi>Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher
<pb facs="tcp:115666:52"/>Love,</hi> late Miniſter of the Goſpel; an uſeful piece.</p>
               <p n="20">20. Heaven and Earth ſhaken, a Treatiſe ſhewing how Kings and Princes, and all other Governments, are turned and changed: by <hi>J. Davis</hi> Miniſter in <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver;</hi> admirably uſeful, and ſeriouſly to be conſidered in theſe times.</p>
               <p n="21">21. The Treaſure of the ſoul, wherein we are taught by dying to ſin to attain to the perfect love of God.</p>
               <p n="22">22. A Treatiſe of Contentation, fit for theſe ſad and troubleſome times: by <hi>I. Hall</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Norwich.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="23">23. Select Thoughts, or choice helps for a pious ſpirit beholding the excellency of her Lord Jeſus: by <hi>I. Hall</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Norwich.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="24">24. The holy Order or Fraternity of Mourners in <hi>Sion;</hi> to which is added, Songs in the Night, or cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs under afflictions: by <hi>I. Hall</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Norwich.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="25">25. The Celeſtiall Lamp, enlightning every di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed ſoul from the depth of everlaſting darkneſſe; by <hi>T. Fotiplace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="26">26. The <hi>Moderate Baptiſt</hi> in two parts, ſhewing the Scripture-way for the Adminiſtring of the Sacrament of Baptiſm, diſcovering the old errour of Original ſin in Babes; by <hi>W. Brittin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="27">27. Dr. <hi>Martin Luther</hi> Treatiſe of Liberty of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; an uſefull Treatiſe for the ſtating Controverſies ſo much diſputed in theſe times about this great point.</p>
               <p n="28">28. The <hi>Key</hi> of <hi>Knowledge;</hi> a little Book by way of Queſtions and Anſwers, intended for the uſe of all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Chriſtians, eſpecially for the Saints of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous familes, by old Mr. <hi>Iohn Iackson</hi> that famous Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine.</p>
               <p n="29">29. The true <hi>Evangelical Temper,</hi> a Treatiſe modeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:115666:52"/>and ſoberly fitted to the preſent grand concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the State and Church, by old Mr. <hi>Iohn Iack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="30">30. The Book of Conſcience opened and read by the ſame Author.</p>
               <p n="31">31. The ſo much deſired and Learned Commentary on the whole 15. Pſalm, by that Reverend and Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Divine Mr. <hi>Chriſtopher Cartwright</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>York,</hi> to which is affixed a brief account of the Authors Life and Work by <hi>R. Bolton.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="32">32. The Judges Charge delivered in a Sermon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Mr. Juſtice <hi>Hall</hi> and Serjeant <hi>Crook</hi> Judges of Aſſize at St. <hi>Mary Overs</hi> in <hi>Southwark,</hi> by <hi>R. Parr</hi> M. A. Paſtor of <hi>Camerwell</hi> in the County of <hi>Surry.</hi> A Sermon worthy peruſall of all ſuch perſons as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to be honeſt and juſt practioners in the Law.</p>
               <p n="33">33. The Saints Tomb-ſtone, being the Life of that Virtuous Gentlewoman Mrs. <hi>Dorothy Shaw,</hi> late Wife of Mr. <hi>Iohn Shaw</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Kingſton</hi> upon <hi>Hull.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Admirable and Learned Treatiſes of Occult Sciences in Philoſophy, Magick, Aſtrology, Geomancy, Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, Phyſiognomy, and Chiromancy.</head>
               <p n="34">34. Magick and Aſtrology vindicated by <hi>H. Warren.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="35">35. <hi>Lux veritatis,</hi> Judicial Aſtrology vindicated, and Demonology confuted: by <hi>W. Ramſey,</hi> Gent.</p>
               <p n="36">36. An Introduction to the Teutonick Philoſophy, being a determination of the Original of the ſoul: by <hi>C. Hotham</hi> Fellow of <hi>Peter-Houſe</hi> in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="37">37. <hi>Cornelius Agrippa</hi> his fourth Book of Occult Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy,
<pb facs="tcp:115666:53"/>or Geomancy; Magical Elements of <hi>Peter de Abona,</hi> the nature of ſpirits, made Engliſh by <hi>R. Turner.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="38">38. <hi>Paracelſus</hi> Occult Philoſophy of the Myſteries of Nature, and his ſecret Alchimy.</p>
               <p n="39">39. An Aſtrological Diſcourſe with Mathematicall Demonſtrations; proving the influence of the Planets and fixed Stars upon Elementary Bodies: by Sir <hi>Chriſt. Heyden</hi> Knight.</p>
               <p n="40">40. <hi>Merlinus Anglicus Junior:</hi> the Engliſh Merlin revived, or a Prediction upon the Affairs of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, for the year 1644. by <hi>W. Lilly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="41">41. Englands Prophetical Merlin, foretelling to all Nations of <hi>Europe,</hi> till 1663. the actions depending upon the Influences of the Conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> 1642. by <hi>W. Lilly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="42">42. The Starry meſſenger, or an interpretation of that ſtrange apparition of three Suns ſeen in <hi>London</hi> the 19. of <hi>November</hi> 1644. being the Birth-day of K. <hi>Charles,</hi> by <hi>W. Lilly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="43">43. The Worlds Cataſtrophe, or <hi>Europes</hi> many mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, untill 1666. by <hi>W. Lilly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="44">44. An Aſtrologicall prediction of the Occurrences in <hi>England,</hi> part in the years 1648. 1649. 1650. by <hi>W. Lilly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="45">45. <hi>Monarchy</hi> or no <hi>Monarchy</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie of the White King, <hi>Grebner</hi> his propheſies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Charles</hi> Son of <hi>Charls</hi> his Greatneſſe, illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with ſeveral Hieroglyphicks, by <hi>W. Lilly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="46">46. <hi>Aunus Tenebraſus,</hi> or the dark year; or Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical judgments upon two Lunary Eclipſes, and one admirable Eclipſe of the Sun in <hi>England,</hi> 1652. by <hi>W. Lilly.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:115666:53"/>
               <p n="47">47. An eaſie and familiar way whereby to judge the effects depending on Eclipſes, by <hi>W. Lilly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="48">48. Supernatural ſights and apparitions ſeen in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, Iune</hi> 30. 1644. by <hi>W. Lilly;</hi> as alſo all his Works in one Volume.</p>
               <p n="49">49. <hi>Cataſtrophe Magnatum,</hi> an Ephemetides for the year 1652. by <hi>N. Culpeper.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="50">50. <hi>Teratologia,</hi> or a diſcovery of Gods Wonders, manifeſted by bloody Rain and Waters: by <hi>J. S.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="51">51. Chyromancy, or the art of divining by the Lines engraven in the hand of man, by dame Nature, in 198. Genitures; with a learned Diſcourſe of the ſoul of the World: by <hi>G. Wharton,</hi> Eſq;</p>
               <p n="52">52. The admired piece of Phyſiognomy, and Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>romancy, Metopoſcopy, the ſymmetrical proportions and ſignal moles of the body, the Interpretation of Dreams, to which is added the art of memory illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Figures: by <hi>R. Sanders, folio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="53">53. The no leſs exquiſite then admirable work, <hi>Theatrum Chemycum Britannicum;</hi> containing ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Poetical pieces of our famous Engliſh Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, who have written the Hermetick myſteries in their own ancient Language; faithfully collected into one Volume, with Annotations thereon: by the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatigable Induſtry of <hi>Elias Aſhmole,</hi> Eſq; illuſtrated with Figures.</p>
               <p n="54">54. The way to Bliſſe, in three Books, a very Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Treatiſe of the Philoſophers Stone, made publick by <hi>Elias Aſhmole,</hi> Eſq;</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:115666:54"/>
               <head>Excellent Treatiſes in the Mathematicks, Geometry, of Arithmetick, Surveying, and other Arts, or Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanicks.</head>
               <p n="55">55. The incomparable Treatiſe of <hi>Tactometria, ſeu Tetagmenometria;</hi> or the Geometry of Regulars, pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctically propoſed after a new &amp; moſt expeditious man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, together with the Natural or Vulgar, by way of menſural compariſon, and in the Solids, not onely in reſpect of Magnitude or Dimenſion, but alſo of Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity or Ponderoſity, according to any metal aſſigned: together with uſefull experiments of meaſures and weights, obſervations on gauging, uſeful for thoſe that are practiſed in the art Metricald: by <hi>T. Wybard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="56">56. <hi>Tectonicon,</hi> ſhewing the exact meaſuring of all manner of Land, Squares, Timber, Stones, Steeples, Pillars, Globes; as alſo the making and uſe of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penters, Rule, &amp;c. fit to be known by all Surveyors, Land-meters, Joyners, Carpenters, and Maſons: by <hi>D. Diggs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="57">57. The unparallell'd work for eaſe and expedition, entituled, The exact Surveyor, or the whole art of ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veying of Land, ſhewing how to plot all manner of grounds, whether ſmall incloſures, champian, plain, wood-lands or mountains, by the plain Table; as alſo how to find the Area, or content of any Land, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect, reduce, or Divide the ſame; as alſo to take the plot or chart, to make a map of any mannor, whether according to <hi>Rathburne,</hi> or any other eminent ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyors method; a Book excellently uſeful for thoſe that ſell, purchaſe, or are otherwiſe employed about Buildings: by <hi>J. Eyre.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:115666:54"/>
               <p n="58">58. The Golden Treatiſe of Arithmetick, Natural and Artificial, or Decimals; the Theory and practiſe united in a ſimpathetical proportion betwixt Line and Numbers, in their Quantities and Qualities, as in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of form, figure, magnitude and affection; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated by Geometry, illuſtrated by Calculations, and confirmed with variety of examples in every Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; made compendious and eaſie for Merchants, Citizens, Seamen, Accomptants, &amp;c. by <hi>Tho. Wilſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> corrector of the laſt Edition of <hi>Record.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="59">59. Semigraphy, or the art of ſhort-writing, as is hath been proved by many hundreds in the City of <hi>London,</hi> and other places by them practiſed, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged to be the eaſieſt, exacteſt and ſwifteſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod; the meaneſt capacity by the help of this Book, with a few hours practice may attain to a perfection in this art: by <hi>J. Rich</hi> Author and teacher thereof, dwelling in <hi>Swithins-Lane</hi> in <hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="60">60. Milk for Children, a plain and eaſie method teaching to read and write, uſeful for Schools and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies: by <hi>J. Thomas</hi> D. D.</p>
               <p n="61">61. The Painting of the ancients, the Hiſtory of the beginning, progreſs, and conſummating of the practiſe of that noble art of painting: by <hi>F. Iunius.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Excellent and approved Treatiſes in Phyſick, Chyrurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and other more familiar Experiments in Cookery, Preſerving, &amp;c.</head>
               <p n="62">62. <hi>Culpeper's Semiatica <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ranica,</hi> his Aſtrological Judgement of Diſeaſes from the decumbiture of the ſick much enlarged: the way and manner of finding
<pb facs="tcp:115666:55"/>out the cauſe, change and end of the Diſeaſe; alſo whether the ſick be likely to live or die, and the time when Recovery or Death is to be expected, according to the judgement of <hi>Hypocrates</hi> and <hi>Hermes Triſme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtus;</hi> to which is added Mr. <hi>Culpepers</hi> cenſure of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines.</p>
               <p n="63">63. <hi>Culpepers</hi> laſt Legacy left to his Wife for the publick good, being the choiceſt and moſt profitable of thoſe ſecrets in Phyſick and Chyrurgery, which whileſt he lived, were lock'd up in his breaſt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved never to be publiſhed till after his death.</p>
               <p n="64">64. The <hi>York-ſhire</hi> Spaw, or the vertue and uſe of that water in curing of deſperate Diſeaſes, with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections and Rules neceſſary to be conſidered by all that repair thither.</p>
               <p n="65">65. Moſt approved Medicines and Remedies for the diſeaſes in the body of man: by <hi>A. Read</hi> Doctor in Phyſick.</p>
               <p n="66">66. The art of ſimpling, an Introduction to the knowledg of gathering of Plants, wherein the defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, diviſions, places, deſcriptions, differences, names, vertues, times, of gathering, temperatures of them, are compendiouſly diſcourſed of: alſo a diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the leſſer World: by <hi>W. Coles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="67">67. Adam in Eden, or Natures Paradiſe: the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of Plants, Hearbs, and Flowers, with their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral original names, the places where they grow, their deſcriptions and kindes, their times of ſlouriſhing and decreaſing; as alſo their ſeveral ſignatures, anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical appropriations, and particular phyſical vertues; with neceſſary obſervations on the ſeaſons of planting and gathering of our Engliſh plants. A work admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb facs="tcp:115666:55"/>uſeful for Apothecaries, Chyrurgeons, and other ingenious perſons, who may in this Herbal find com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized all the Engliſh phyſical ſimples, that <hi>Gerard</hi> or <hi>Parkinſon</hi> in their two voluminous Herbals have diſcourſed of; even ſo as to be on emergent occaſions their own Phyſicians, the Ingredients being to be had in their own Fields and Gardens: publiſhed for the general good, by <hi>W. Coles</hi> M.D.</p>
               <p n="68">68. The complete midwives practiſe in the high and weighty concernments of the body of mankinde: the ſecond Edition corrected and enlarged, with a full ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of ſuch moſt uſeful and admirable ſecrets which Mr. <hi>Nicholas Culpeper</hi> in his brief Treatiſe, and other Engliſh Writers in the art of Midwifry have hitherto wilfully paſſed by, kept cloſe to themſelves, or wholly omitted: by <hi>T. Chamberlaine,</hi> M. P. illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Copper Figures.</p>
               <p n="69">69. The Queens Cloſet opened, incomparable ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets in phyſick, chyrurgery, preſerving, candying, and cookery; as they were preſented to the Queen by the moſt experienced perſons of our times; many where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of were honoured with her own practiſe.</p>
               <p n="70">70. <hi>William Clows</hi> his Chirurgical Obſervations for thoſe that are burned with the flames of Gun-pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as alſo for the curing of wounds and <hi>lues venerea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="71">71. The expert Doctors Diſpenſatory, the whole art of Phyſick reſtored to practice, with a ſurvey of moſt Diſpenſatories extant; a work for the plainneſs and method not to be parallell'd by any, with a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face of Mr. <hi>Nich. Culpepers</hi> to the Reader in its com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation: by <hi>P. Morebius,</hi> Phyſician to the King: <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:115666:56"/>
               <p n="72">72. The perfect Cook, a right method in the art of Cookery, whether for Paſtry or <hi>A la mode</hi> Kickſhaws, with 55. wayes of dreſſing Eggs: by <hi>M. M.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Elegant Treatiſes in Humanity, Hiſtory, Deſcription of Countries, Romances and Poetry.</head>
               <p n="73">73. Times Treaſury or Academy, for the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of the Engliſh Gentry in arguments of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, Habit, Faſhion, Behaviour, &amp;c. all ſummed up in characters of Honour: by <hi>R. Brathwait</hi> Eſq;</p>
               <p n="74">74. <hi>Oedipus,</hi> or the Reſolver of the ſecrets of Love and other natural problems, by way of Queſtion and Anſwer.</p>
               <p n="75">75. The admirable and moſt impartiall Hiſtory of <hi>New England,</hi> of the firſt plantation there in the year 1628. brought down to theſe times: all the material paſſages performed there, exactly related.</p>
               <p n="76">76. <hi>America</hi> painted to the Life, the Hiſtory of the Conqueſt, and firſt Original undertaking of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of plantation in thoſe parts, with an exact Map: by <hi>F. Gorges,</hi> Eſq;</p>
               <p n="77">77. The tears of the Indians, the Hiſtory of the moſt bloody and moſt cruel proceedings of the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards in the Iſlands of <hi>Hiſpaniola, Cuba, Jamaica, Mexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co, Peru,</hi> and other places of the Weſt-Indies; in which to the life are diſcovered the tyrannies of the Spaniards, as alſo the juſtneſſe of our War ſo ſucceſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully managed againſt them.</p>
               <p n="78">78. The Illuſtrious Shepherdeſſe. The Imperious Brother, written origionally in Spaniſh by that Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Wit, <hi>Don Iohn Perez de Montalbans;</hi> tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:115666:56"/>at the requeſts of the Marchioneſs of <hi>Dorcheſter,</hi> and the Counteſs of <hi>Strafford:</hi> by <hi>E. P.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="79">79. The Hiſtory of the golden Aſs, as alſo the Loves of <hi>Cupid</hi> and his Miſtreſſe <hi>Pſiche:</hi> by <hi>L. Apuleius,</hi> tranſlated into Engliſh.</p>
               <p n="80">80. The Unfortunate Mother, a Tragedy, by <hi>T. N.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="81">81. The Rebellion: a Comedy, by <hi>T. Rawlins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="82">82. The Tragedy of <hi>Meſſalina</hi> the inſatiate Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Empreſs: by <hi>N. Richards.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="83">83. The Floating Iſland: a Trage-Comedy acted before the King, by the Students of <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> in <hi>Oxon.</hi> by that Renowned Wit <hi>W. Strode;</hi> the ſongs were ſet by Mr. <hi>Henry Lawes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="84">84. <hi>Harvey's</hi> Divine Poems, the Hiſtory of <hi>Balaam,</hi> of <hi>Ionah,</hi> and of St. <hi>Iohn</hi> the Evangeliſt.</p>
               <p n="85">85. <hi>Fons Lachrymarum,</hi> or a Fountain of tears; the Lamentations of the Prophet <hi>Ieremiah</hi> in Verſe, with an Elegy on Sir <hi>Charles Lucas:</hi> by <hi>I. Quarles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="86">86. Nocturnal Lucubrations, with other witty E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pigrams and Epitaphs: by <hi>R. Chamberlain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="87">87. The admirable ingenuous Satyr againſt Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites.</p>
               <p n="88">88. Wit Reſtored, in ſeverall ſelect Poems, not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly publiſhed by Sr. <hi>Iohn Menis</hi> and Mr. <hi>Smith,</hi> with others.</p>
               <p n="89">89. Sportive Wit, the Muſes meriment, a new Spring of Drollery, Jovill Fancies, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Poetical, with ſeveral other accurately ingenuous Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes lately printed.</head>
               <p n="90">90. Wits Interpreter, the Engliſh Parnaſſus: or a
<pb facs="tcp:115666:57"/>ſure Guide to thoſe admirable accompliſhments that complete the Engliſh Gentry, in the moſt acceptable Qualifications of diſcourſe or writing. An art of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick, accurate Complements, Fancies, Deviſes, and Experiments, Poems, Poetical Fictions, and <hi>A la mode</hi> Letters: by <hi>I.C.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="91">91. Wit and Drollery, with other Jovial Poems with new additions: by Sir <hi>I.M.M.L.M.S.W.D.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="92">92. The conveyance of Light, or the complete Clerk and Scriveners guide; being an exact draught of all preſidents and aſſurances now in uſe; as they were penned and perfected by divers Learned Judges, Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Lawyers, and great Conveyancers, both ancient and modern: whereunto is added a Concordance from King <hi>Richard</hi> the Third to this preſent.</p>
               <p n="93">93. <hi>Themis Aurea,</hi> the Laws of the Fraternity of the <hi>Roſie Croſs;</hi> in which the occult ſecrets of their Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophical Notions are brought to light: written by <hi>Count Mayerus,</hi> and now Engliſhed by <hi>T. H.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="94">94. The Iron Rod put into the Lord Protectors hand; a Prophetical Treatiſe.</p>
               <p n="95">95. <hi>Medicina Magica tamen Phyſica,</hi> magical but na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural phyſick, containing the general cures of Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties &amp; diſeaſes belonging to the bodies of men, as alſo to other animals and domeſtick Creatures, by way of tranſplantation, with a deſcription of the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Cordial out of Gold by <hi>Sam. Boulton</hi> of <hi>Salop.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="96">96. <hi>I. Tradeſcant's</hi> Rarities publiſh'd by himſelf.</p>
               <p n="97">97. The proceedings of the High Court of Juſtice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the late King <hi>Charles,</hi> with his ſpeech upon the Scaffold and other proceedings, <hi>Ian.</hi> 30. 1648.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:115666:57"/>
               <head>Admirable Uſefull Treatiſes newly printed.</head>
               <p n="98">98. Natures Secrets, or the admirable and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Hiſtory of the generation of meteors, deſcribing the temperatures of the elements, the heights, magnitudes and influences of Stars, the cauſes of Comets, Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes, Deluges, Epidemical Diſeaſes, and prodigies of precedent times: with preſages of the weather, and deſcriptions of the weather-glaſs: by <hi>T. Wilsford.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="99">99. The myſteries of Love and Eloquence, or the arts of Wooing and Complementing, as they are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged in the <hi>Spring-Garden, Hide Park,</hi> the <hi>New Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,</hi> and other eminent places: A work in which is drawn to the life the Deportments of the moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh'd perſons: the mode of their Courtly enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments, treatment of their Ladies at Balls, their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed Sports, Drolls and Fancies, the Witchcrafts of their perſwaſive Language in their approaches, or other more ſecret diſpatches, &amp;c. by <hi>E.P.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="100">100. <hi>Helmont</hi> diſguiſed, or the vulgar errors of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial and unskilful practiſers of phyſick confuted, more eſpecially as they concern the Cures of Feavers, the Stone, the plague, and ſome other Diſeaſes by way of Dialogue, in which the chief rarities of phyſick are admirably diſcourſed of: by <hi>I.T.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Books in the Preſs and now printing.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Geometry demonſtrated by lines and numbers; from thence Aſtronomy, Coſmography and Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion proved and delineated by the doctrine of plain
<pb facs="tcp:115666:58"/>and ſpherical Triangles: by <hi>T. Willsford.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The Engliſh Annals, from the Invaſion made by <hi>Julius Ceſar</hi> to theſe times: by <hi>T. Willsford.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The Fool transformed, a Comedy.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Hiſtory of <hi>Lewis</hi> the eleventh King of <hi>France,</hi> a Trage-comedy.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The chaſte Woman againſt her will, a Comedy.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The Tooth-drawer, a Comedy.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Honour in the end, a Comedy.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Tell-tale, a Comedy.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The Hiſtory of <hi>Donquixot,</hi> or the Knight of the ill-favoured face, a Comedy.</p>
               <p n="10">10. The fair Spaniſh Captive, a Trage-comedy.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Sir <hi>Kenelm Digby,</hi> and other Perſons of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, their rare and incomparable ſecrets of Phyſick, Chirurgery, Cookery, Preſerving, Conſerving, Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying, diſtilling of Waters, extraction of Oyls, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding of the coſtlieſt Perfumes, with other admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable inventions and ſelect experiments, as they offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red themſelves to their obſervations, whether here or in forreign Countries.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Books lately printed.</head>
               <p n="12">12. The ſo well entertained work, the New World of Engliſh words, or a general Dictionary, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Terms, Etymologies, Definitions, and perfect Interpretations of the proper ſignifications of hard Engliſh words, throughout the Arts and Sciences Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral or Mechanick; as alſo other ſubjects that are uſeful or appertain to the Language of our Nation: to which is added the ſignification of proper Names,
<pb facs="tcp:115666:58"/>Mythology and Poetical Fictions, Hiſtorical Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Geographical Deſcriptions of the Countries and Cities of the world, eſpecially of theſe three Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, wherein their chiefeſt Antiquities, Battles, and other moſt remarkable paſſages are mentioned: a work very neceſſary for ſtrangers as well as our own countrymen, for all perſons that would rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what they diſcourſe or read: collected and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by <hi>E.P.</hi> for the greater honour of thoſe learned Gentlemen and Artiſts that have been aſſiſtant in the moſt practical Sciences, their names are preſented be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Book.</p>
               <p n="13">13. The modern Aſſurancer, the Clerks Directory, containing the practick part of the Law, in the exact forms and draughts of all manner of Preſidents for Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gains and Sales, Grants, Feoffments, Bonds, Bills, Conditions, Covenants, Joyntures, Indentures, to lead the uſes of Fines and Recoveries, with good Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſo's and Covenants to ſtand ſeiſed, Charter-parties for Ships, Leaſes, Releaſes, Surrenders, &amp;c. and all other Inſtruments and Aſſurances now in uſe, inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for all young Students and Practicers of the Law: by <hi>John Hern.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. <hi>Moor's</hi> Arithmetick, the ſecond Edition, much refined and diligently cleared from the former miſtakes of the preſs; a work containing the whole art of Arithmetick as well in numbers as ſpecies, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with many additions by the Author, is come forth.</p>
               <p n="15">15. Likewiſe <hi>Exercitatio Eleiptica Nova,</hi> or a new Mathematical Contemplation on the Oval Figure cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led an <hi>Eleipſis;</hi> together with the two firſt Books of
<pb facs="tcp:115666:59"/>
                  <hi>Mydorgius</hi> his Conicks Analiz'd and made ſo plain, that the Doctrine of Conical ſections may be eaſily underſtood; a Work much deſired and never before publiſhed in the Engliſh Tongue: by <hi>Ionas Moor,</hi> Surveyor Generall of the great Levell of the <hi>Fennes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. Naps upon Parnaſſus, a ſleepy muſe nipt and pinch'd though not awakened: ſuch Voluntary and Jovial Copies of Verſes as were lately receiv'd from ſome of the Wits of the Univerſities in a Frolick; Dedicated to <hi>Gondiberts</hi> Miſtreſſe, by Captain <hi>Iones</hi> and others. Whereunto is added for Demonſtration of the Authors Proſaick Excellencies, his Epiſtle to one of the Univerſities, with the Anſwer; together with two Satyrical Characters of his own, of a Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizer, and an Antiquary, with marginal notes by a Friend to the Reader.</p>
               <p n="17">17. <hi>Culpepers</hi> School of Phyſick, or the Experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal practiſe of the whole Art, ſo reduced either into Aphoriſmes, or choice and tryed Receipts, that the free-born Students of the three Kingdoms may in this method find perfect ways for the operation of ſuch me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, ſo Aſtrologically and Phyſically preſcribed, as that they may themſelves be competent Judges of the Cures of their patients: by <hi>N. C.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="18">18. <hi>Blagrave's</hi> admirable Ephemerides for the year 1659. and 1660.</p>
               <p n="19">19. <hi>J. Cleaveland</hi> Revived, Poems, Orations, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles, and other of his Genuine incomparable pieces: a ſecond impreſſion with many additions.</p>
               <p n="20">20. The Exquiſite Letters of Maſter <hi>Robert Love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> the late admired Tranſlatour of the Volumes of
<pb facs="tcp:115666:59"/>the famed Romance <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> for the perpetuating his memory; publiſhed by his dear Brother, Mr. <hi>A. L.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="21">21. <hi>Englands</hi> Worthies, Select Lives of 47. moſt Eminent perſons from <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great to the late times: by <hi>W. Winſtanley,</hi> Gent.</p>
               <p n="22">22. The Accompliſh'd Cook, the Myſtery of the whole Art of Cookery revealed in a more eaſie and perfect method then hath been publiſh'd in any Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage; expert and ready ways for the dreſſing of Fleſh, Fowl, and Fiſh, the raiſing of Paſtes, the beſt directions for all manner of Kickſhaws, and the moſt poinant Sauces, with the terms of carving and ſew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: the Bills of Fare, and exact account of all diſhes for the ſeaſon, with other <hi>A la mode</hi> Curiofities, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the lively Illuſtrations of ſuch neceſſary fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures as are referred to practiſe: approved by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years experience, and carefull induſtry of <hi>Robert May,</hi> in the time of his attendance on ſeveral perſons of Honour.</p>
               <p n="23">23. The Scales of Commerce and Trade, the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery revealed as to traffick with a Debitor or Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, for Merchants Accounts after the Italian way, and eaſieſt method; as alſo a Treatiſe of Architecture, and a computation as to all the charges of building: by <hi>T. Wilsford,</hi> Gent.</p>
               <p n="24">24. Arts Maſter-piece, or the beautifying part of phyſick; whereby all defects of Nature of both ſexes are amended, age renewed, youth continued, and all imperfections fairly remedied: by <hi>B. T.</hi> Doctor of phyſick.</p>
               <p n="25">25. A Diſcourſe concerning Liberty of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, in which are contained propoſals about what
<pb facs="tcp:115666:60"/>liberty in this kind is now politically expedient to be given, and ſeveral reaſons to ſhew how much the peace and welfare is concerned therein: by <hi>R.T.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="26">26. Chriſtian Reformation, being an earneſt ſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the ſpeedy practice of it: propoſed to all, but eſpecially deſigned for the ſerious conſideration of my dear Kindred and countrymen of the County of <hi>Cork</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the people of <hi>Riegat</hi> and <hi>Camerwell</hi> in the County of <hi>Surrey:</hi> by <hi>Richard Parr,</hi> Doctor in Divinity there.</p>
               <p n="27">27. The Character of <hi>Spain,</hi> or an Epitomy of their Vertues and Vices.</p>
               <p n="28">28. The Character of <hi>Italy,</hi> or the Italian anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mized by an Engliſh Chirurgion.</p>
               <p n="29">29. The Character of <hi>France,</hi> to which is added <hi>Gallus caſtratus,</hi> or an Anſwer to a pamphlet called <hi>The character of England,</hi> as alſo a freſh Whip for the Monſieur in anſwer to his Letter: the ſecond Edit.</p>
               <p n="30">30. No neceſſity of Reformation of the publick Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> by <hi>Iohn Pear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> D.D.</p>
               <p n="31">31. An Anſwer to Dr. <hi>Burges's</hi> Word by way of poſtſcript, in vindication of No Neceſſity of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the publick Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> by <hi>Iohn Pearſon</hi> D.D.</p>
               <p n="32">32. A Treatiſe of peace between the two viſible di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided parties; wherein is inquired, What peace is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, who the parties that differ, wherein the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference conſiſts, how they fell out, wherein they ought to agree, how they may be perſwaded unto peace, by what means reconciliation may be made between them.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:115666:60"/>
               <p n="33">33. Dr. <hi>Daniel Featly</hi> Revived, proving that the Proteſtant Church, and not the Catholick, is the only viſible and true Church; in a Manual preſerved from the hands of the plunderers, with a ſuccinct Hiſtory of his life and death: publiſhed by <hi>Iohn Featly,</hi> Chaplain to the Kings moſt excellent Majeſty.</p>
               <p n="34">34. <hi>Scotch</hi> Covenant condemned, being a full an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to Mr. <hi>Duglas</hi> his Sermon, preached at the Kings Coronation in <hi>Scotland,</hi> wherein His Sacred Majeſty is vindicated: by a loyal and orthodox hand.</p>
               <p n="35">35. <hi>Englands Tryumph,</hi> a more exact Hiſtory of His Majeſties Eſcape after the Battle of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> with a Chronological diſcourſe of His Straits and Dangerous Adventures into <hi>France,</hi> and His Removes from place to place till His return into <hi>England,</hi> with the moſt Remarkable Memorials till <hi>September</hi> laſt.</p>
               <p n="36">36. <hi>Euclides</hi> Elements in 15. Books in Engliſh, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated by <hi>Mr. Barrow</hi> of <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="37">37. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <hi>God</hi> made <hi>Man.</hi> A Tract pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Nativity of our Saviour to be on the 25. of <hi>December:</hi> by <hi>I. Selden.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe are to give notice, that the true and right Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zenges and Pectorals ſo generally known and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of for the cure of Conſumptions, Coughs, Aſtama's, Colds in general, and all other Diſeaſes incident to the Head, are rightly made onely by <hi>Iohn Piercy,</hi> Gent. the firſt Inventor of them; and whoſoever maketh them beſides, do but counterfeit them: they are to be ſold by <hi>Nath. Brook</hi> at the Angel in <hi>Cornhill.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
